<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"
    xml:id="frus1977-80v26">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume
                    XXVI, Arms Control and Nonproliferation</title>
                <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
                <title type="subseries">1977–1980</title>
                <title type="volumenumber">Volume XXVI</title>
                <title type="volume">Arms Control and Nonproliferation</title>
                <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
                <editor role="primary">Chris Tudda</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>United States Government Printing Office</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <idno type="frus">frus1977-80v26</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Released in 2015 as print volume and PDF online at history.state.gov</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage type="main">
                <pb n="I" facs="0002" xml:id="pg_I"/>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subseries">1977–1980</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="volumeno">Volume XXVI</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="volumetitle">Arms Control and Nonproliferation</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>: <name>Chris Tudda</name>
                </byline>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="italic">General Editor</hi>: <name>Adam M. Howard</name>
                </byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <publisher>United States Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
                    <docDate>2015</docDate>
                    <pb n="II" facs="0003" xml:id="pg_II"/>DEPARTMENT OF STATE O<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ffice</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">the</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">istorian</hi> B<hi
                        rend="smallcaps">ureau</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">ublic</hi> A<hi
                        rend="smallcaps">ffairs</hi> For sale by the Superintendent of Documents,
                    U.S. Government Printing Office Internet: bookstore.gpo.gov Phone: toll free
                    (866) 512-1800; DC area (202) 512-1800 Fax: (202) 512-2250 Mail: Stop IDCC,
                    Washington, DC 20402-0001 </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div xml:id="pressrelease" type="section">
                <head>Press Release</head>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="strong">Office of the Historian<lb/>Bureau of Public
                        Affairs<lb/>United States Department of State<lb/>November 19, 2015</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State released today <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi>, 1977–1980, Volume XXVI, Arms Control and
                    Nonproliferation. This volume documents the Carter administration’s
                    multilateral, non-strategic arms control policy from 1977 until 1980. Topics
                    include anti-satellite (ASAT) talks; chemical and biological warfare
                    negotiations; conventional arms talks (CAT); nuclear non-proliferation,
                    safeguards, and the International Fuel Cycle Evaluation program; comprehensive
                    nuclear test-ban proposals and peaceful nuclear explosions; the United Nations
                    Special Session on Disarmament; and nuclear non-proliferation in Latin
                    America.</p>
                <p>The Carter administration’s priorities in arms control contrasted sharply with
                    those of the Nixon and Ford administrations. Where his predecessors had
                    concentrated on bilateral arms control negotiations with the Soviet Union,
                    Carter aggressively pursued a range of multilateral agreements, with a strong
                    emphasis on nonproliferation in nuclear and conventional arms. While Moscow
                    remained the administration’s primary interlocutor, Carter worked closely with
                    the United Kingdom to try to achieve a comprehensive nuclear test ban treaty. He
                    also worked with Mexico to convince other Latin American nations to sign and/or
                    ratify the Treaty of Tlatelolco—which had established Latin America as a
                    nuclear-free zone in 1968. In conjunction with France, Japan, and other allies,
                    Carter proposed the establishment of an International Fuel Cycle Evaluation
                    program that would explore alternative nuclear fuel cycles containing materials
                    not useable in nuclear weapons. The Carter administration also participated in
                    multilateral arms control initiatives such as the 1978 UN Special Session on
                    Disarmament. Meanwhile, Carter tried to reduce the sale of conventional arms to
                    allies with questionable human rights records.</p>
                <p>By the winter of 1979–80, however, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and other
                    Soviet activities jeopardized Carter’s arms control initiatives. Reports of the
                    use of chemical weapons by the Soviets in Afghanistan and Vietnam in Cambodia
                    and Laos, the discovery of a 1979 outbreak of anthrax in a biological weapons
                    factory in Sverdlovsk in the Soviet Union, and renewed Soviet nuclear tests led
                    to administration protests that the Soviets had violated the 1972 Biological
                    Weapons Convention and 1976 Threshold Test Ban Treaties respectively. The ASAT
                    and CAT negotiations principally ended in early 1980, and the volume of U.S.
                    conventional arms sales remained essentially unchanged during the
                    administration.</p>
                <p>This volume was compiled and edited by Chris Tudda. The volume and this press
                    release are available on the Office of the Historian website at <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1977-80v26"
                        >http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1977-80v26</ref>. Copies
                    of the volume will be available for purchase from the U.S. Government Printing
                    Office online at <ref target="http://bookstore.gpo.gov"
                        >http://bookstore.gpo.gov</ref> GPO S/N 044-000-02673-2; ISBN
                    978-0-16-093099-7), or by calling toll-free 1-866-512-1800 (D.C. area
                    202-512-1800). For further information, contact <ref
                        target="mailto:history@state.gov">history@state.gov</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <!--<div xml:id="preface" type="section"/>
                <div xml:id="sources" type="section"/>
                <div xml:id="terms" type="section"/>
                <div xml:id="persons" type="section"/>-->
        </front>
        <body/>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
