<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0" xml:id="frus1969-76ve11p1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume
                    E–11, Part 1, Documents on Mexico; Central America; and the Caribbean,
                    1973–1976</title>
                <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
                <title type="subseries">1969–1976</title>
                <title type="volumenumber">Volume E–11, Part 1</title>
                <title type="volume">Documents on Mexico; Central America; Caribbean,
                    1973–1976</title>
                <editor role="primary">Halbert Jones</editor>
                <editor role="primary">Douglas Kraft</editor>
                <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Office of the Historian, Bureau of Public Affairs, U.S. Department of
                    State</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
                <date>2015</date>
                <idno type="frus">frus1969-76ve11p1</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Released in 2015 as HTML/PDF online at history.state.gov</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>The following errors in the original edition have been corrected: <list>
                            <item/>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>2015-06-02 PA/HO MC: Created volume shell.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage type="main">
                <figure> </figure>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subseries">1969–1976</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="volumenumber">Volume E–11, Part 1</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="volume">Documents on Mexico; Central America; Caribbean,
                        1973–1976</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>Department of State<lb/>Washington</docImprint>
                <byline>Editors: <persName>Halbert Jones</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Douglas Kraft</persName></byline>
                <byline>General Editor: <persName>Adam M. Howard</persName>
                </byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <publisher>Office of the Historian<lb/>Bureau of Public Affairs<lb/>U.S.
                        Department of State</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Washington</pubPlace>
                    <docDate>2015</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="section" xml:id="pressrelease">
                <head>Press Release</head>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="strong">Office of the Historian<lb/>Bureau of Public Affairs
                        <lb/>United States Department of State<lb/>June 3, 2015</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State released today <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi>, subseries that documents the most important issues in
                    the foreign policy of Presidents Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. The volume
                    on American Republics has been divided into two parts: Part One, this volume,
                    documents the formulation of a new U.S. policy towards the region as a whole and
                    bilateral relations with fourteen countries and one British possession—The
                    Bahamas, Barbados, Belize, Costa Rica, Cuba, the Dominican Republic, El
                    Salvador, Grenada, Guatemala, Guyana, Haiti, Honduras, Jamaica, Mexico, and
                    Nicaragua—during the second Nixon and Ford administrations; Part Two,
                    forthcoming, documents bilateral relations with countries in South America. </p>
                <p>U.S. policy towards Latin America during this period centered on establishing
                    what Henry A. Kissinger called a “New Dialogue” with the region. Launched in
                    October 1973, just days after Kissinger took office as Secretary of State, the
                    “New Dialogue” was envisioned as a constructive way for the United States to
                    meet the challenge posed by the perceived emergence of a Latin American regional
                    bloc. The initiative called for regular meetings of foreign ministers to address
                    issues of mutual concern and aimed to restore a sense that a special
                    relationship existed between the United States and its neighbors to the south.
                    By 1976, however, U.S. officials had largely abandoned the idea of pursuing a
                    unified regional policy, as called for by the “New Dialogue.” Instead,
                    recognizing that Latin America was not a monolithic bloc, the Ford
                    administration focused more on bilateral relations with the nations of the
                    hemisphere. As this volume documents, during the Nixon and Ford administrations
                    immigration and narcotics control emerged as key issues in bilateral relations,
                    particularly with Mexico. Other themes that occur are water salinity, economic
                    concerns, and investment disputes. Finally, military regimes controlled many
                    Central American governments during the 1970s, and some early hints of the
                    unrest that generated the civil wars of the 1980s appear in the documents in
                    this volume. </p>

                <p>This volume was compiled and edited by Halbert Jones and Douglas Kraft, and is
                    available exclusively on the Office of the Historian website at <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76ve11p1"
                        >http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76ve11p1</ref>. For
                    further information, contact Adam Howard, General Editor of the Foreign
                    Relations series, at (202) 955–0202 or by e-mail to history@state.gov.</p>
            </div>
            <!--<div xml:id="preface" type="section"/>
            <div xml:id="sources" type="section"/>
            <div xml:id="terms" type="section"/>
            <div xml:id="persons" type="section"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="actionsstatement"/>-->


        </front>
        <body/>
        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
