<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v18">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XVIII, Middle
        East Region; Arabian Peninsula</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Middle East Region; Arabian Peninsula</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kelly M. McFarland</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-092999-1</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2015</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2015</published-year>
    <published-date>2015-08-19</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1981</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">42</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">935</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As part of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign
                Relations</tei:hi> subseries devoted to the foreign policy of the administration of
            President Jimmy Carter, this volume documents the Carter administration’s approach to
            the Middle East region in response to the shifting political landscape in Southwest Asia
            at the end of the 1970s. It covers the broad range of issues which shaped and influenced
            the administration’s policies toward the region as a whole, including developments in
            the Gulf and the western Indian Ocean, as well as U.S. bilateral relations with the
            Arabian Peninsula countries and Iraq. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Carter administration focused initially
            on strengthening relationships with partners like Saudi Arabia, cultivating new
            relationships with the newly-independent Gulf states, and re-establishing dialogues with
            the Yemen Arab Republic and Iraq. However, the end of the Shah of Iran’s rule at the
            beginning of 1979 and the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in December of that year
            prompted the administration to raise U.S. strategic engagement in the region. For
            officials, these events highlighted the need for a more robust U.S. military presence
            and security framework to meet the challenges of the new security environment across
            Southwest Asia and the northern arc of the Indian Ocean. President Carter articulated
            this new imperative in his January 1980 State of the Union address, in which he pledged
            that the United States would use military force to protect its interests in the Middle
            East, a position which became known popularly as the “Carter Doctrine.” Throughout the
            remainder of his time in office, Carter and his foreign policy advisers strove to
            increase U.S. military presence in Southwest Asia and to seek greater access and basing
            rights across the region.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
