<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v01">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume I, Foundations
        of Foreign Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Foundations of Foreign Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume I</title>
    <editor role="primary">Louis J. Smith</editor>
    <editor role="primary">David H. Herschler</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/i/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2003</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">20</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">427</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The purpose of this volume, which is a
            departure from previous volumes published in the Foreign Relations series, is to
            document the intellectual foundations of the foreign policy of the first Nixon
            administration. Previous volumes have been compiled to meet the legislatively mandated
            standard that the Foreign Relations series shall be "a thorough, accurate, and reliable
            documentary record of major United States foreign policy decisions and significant
            diplomatic activity." This volume is unique in that it explores the collective mind-set
            of the Nixon administration on foreign policy issues rather than documenting foreign
            policy decisions or diplomatic exchanges. It takes as its canvas the entire record of
            the first Nixon administration. Therefore the documents selected are necessarily a
            sampling chosen to illustrate policy perspectives and themes, rather than a thorough
            record of a bilateral relationship or of a major issue. A measure of the departure of
            this volume from previous volumes in the Foreign Relations series is the extent to which
            it draws upon the published record of speeches, press releases, press conferences and
            briefings, interviews, and testimony before Congressional committees to document policy
            positions and the assumptions of administration officials on the foreign policy process. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">President Nixon had a strong interest in
            foreign policy and he and his assistant for National Security Affairs, Henry Kissinger
            managed many of the more important aspects of foreign policy from the White House. Nixon
            and Kissinger shared a well-defined general perception of world affairs. The editors of
            the volume sought to present a representative selection of documents chosen to develop
            the primary intellectual themes that ran through and animated the administration's
            foreign policy. The documents selected focus heavily upon the perspectives of Nixon and
            Kissinger but also include those of Secretary of State Rogers, Secretary of Defense
            Laird, Under Secretary of State Richardson and others. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
