<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v31">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXXI, Foreign
        Economic Policy, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXXI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160844102</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2009</published-year>
    <published-date>2010-12-23</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">29</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1111</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a subseries of volumes
            of the Foreign Relations series that documents the most important issues in the foreign
            policy of the administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. This volume
            documents U.S. foreign economic policy from 1973 to 1976, focusing on international
            monetary policy, economic summitry, trade policy, commodity policy, and North-South
            relations.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume has a tightly defined
            understanding of foreign economic policy, one that focuses on three significant areas:
            international monetary relations, international trade, and efforts to redress global
            economic inequalities. The section on international monetary policy and economic
            summitry focuses on the aftermath of the collapse of the fixed exchange rate regime
            envisioned at the 1944 Bretton Woods conference. It includes documents on the monetary
            crisis of February and March 1973; efforts to reform the international monetary system,
            with particular emphasis on the issues of exchange rate flexibility and the future of
            gold; and the creation of the G–7 summit. The section on trade policy, more than any
            other section in this volume, demonstrates the influence of domestic politics on foreign
            economic policy; this is particularly clear in the documents on the 1973 decision to
            impose export controls and the White House’s efforts to secure passage of a major piece
            of trade reform legislation, the Trade Act of 1974. This section also includes documents
            on the beginnings of a new round of negotiations under the General Agreement on Tariffs
            and Trade, with particular emphasis on the role of agriculture in those negotiations, as
            well as foreign fears of U.S. protectionism. The final section, on commodity policy and
            North-South issues, documents the approach of the Nixon and Ford administrations to the
            persistent economic disparities between the industrialized nations of the North and the
            less developed countries of the South; it also explores U.S. attempts to grapple with
            the global trade in primary commodities in a post-1973 oil embargo world.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
