<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v09">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume IX,
        Arab-Israeli Dispute, August 1978–December 1980</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Arab-Israeli Dispute, August 1978–December 1980</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume IX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Alexander R. Wieland</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160926594</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2014</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2014</published-year>
    <published-date>2014-12-18</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1404</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As part of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign
                Relations</tei:hi> subseries devoted to the foreign policy of the administration of
            President Jimmy Carter, this volume is the second of two volumes that document U.S.
            efforts to achieve a negotiated settlement to the Arab-Israeli dispute. This volume
            begins with the August 1978 acceptance by Egyptian President Anwar al-Sadat and Israeli
            Prime Minister Menachem Begin of President Carter’s invitation to attend a tripartite
            summit meeting at Camp David. It traces the course of the September 1978 Camp David
            Summit and the series of negotiations which followed, talks which culminated in the
            conclusion of the Egyptian-Israeli Peace Treaty on March 26, 1979. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">During this period, the Arab-Israeli dispute
            was top on the list of U.S. foreign policy priorities, reflected in President Carter’s
            direct involvement in the peace process. With the U.S. failure to broaden Arab support
            for its diplomatic efforts and the pressures caused by a growing number of crises
            elsewhere, the administration’s engagement with the Arab-Israeli dispute entered a less
            intensive phase after the spring of 1979. The volume concludes by documenting the
            administration’s ultimately unsuccessful attempt to build upon the Egyptian-Israeli
            Treaty and address the situation in the West Bank and Gaza Strip. During the last
            eighteen months of the administration, U.S. diplomacy toward this issue focused on
            keeping the faltering autonomy negotiations on track, securing the continued goodwill
            and stability of Egypt, mediating Sadat’s public rivalries with other Arab countries,
            dealing with the upheaval in Lebanon, and addressing the series of resolutions related
            to the Arab-Israeli dispute brought before the United Nations. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
