<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v11">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XI, South Asia
        Crisis, 1971</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">South Asia Crisis, 1971</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Louis J. Smith</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/xi/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2005</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">33</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">900</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The scope of this volume is limited to the
            political crisis that began in Pakistan in March 1971 with the government's efforts to
            suppress Bengali demands for virtual autonomy in East Pakistan and concluded with the
            establishment of the state of Bangladesh at the end of the year. The limited time frame
            covered by the volume enabled the editor to compile the record of the Nixon
            administration's response to the crisis in considerable detail. The crisis was managed
            largely out of the White House by President Nixon and his Assistant for National
            Security Affairs Henry Kissinger, with the support of the National Security Council
            staff. The focus of the volume is on the management of the crisis by Nixon and
            Kissinger. The editor selected documentation to trace the evolution of the United States
            response to the crisis from Nixon's initial reluctance to become involved to his "tilt"
            toward Pakistan which was highlighted by the despatch of the aircraft carrier Enterprise
            to the Bay of Bengal to act as a restraint on India in the war that had developed
            between India and Pakistan as a result of the crisis. Nixon's response to the crisis in
            Pakistan was conditioned in part by the concern that he and Kissinger had to protect the
            emerging opening to China, which had been facilitated by Pakistani President Yahya Khan.
            The volume documents that concern, as well as the assurance offered to China that the
            United States would protect China from the Soviet Union if China took military action
            against India in support of Pakistan. The record of the Nixon administration's
            management of the crisis in South Asia thus also bears importantly on United States
            relations at the time with China and the Soviet Union. In that respect, the volume
            should be read in conjunction with Foreign Relations, 1969–1976, volume XVII, China,
            1969–1972; volume XIII, Soviet Union, October 1970–October 1971; and volume XIV, Soviet
            Union, October 1971–May 1971.</tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>joewiz</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>joewiz</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>chalouma</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-08-30T11:00:50.667-05:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
