<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v04">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume IV, National
        Security Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">National Security Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume IV</title>
    <editor role="primary">James G. Wilson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-095832-8</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2024</published-year>
    <published-date>2024-03-06</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1976</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1981</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">23</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">944</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a subseries of volumes
            of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that documents the
            foreign policy decision making of the administration of President Jimmy Carter. It
            focuses on the Carter administration’s efforts to modernize U.S. nuclear and
            conventional forces; undertake a comprehensive net assessment of the global balance of
            power; craft national security strategies; sustain the NATO alliance; preserve
            telecommunications security; devise a system for crisis management; prepare for national
            emergencies; and update nuclear war planning. Documentation is also included on budget
            decisions that initially reflected the Carter administration’s efforts to cut spending
            without damaging national security.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">At the core of this volume is the Carter
            administration’s efforts to reduce the prospects of a nuclear war. While the president
            aspired to sign arms control agreements that he hoped would deaccelerate the nuclear
            arms race, he and top members of his administration also wanted to strengthen nuclear
            deterrence with respect to the Soviet Union amidst relentless domestic political
            criticism—and allied concern—that they were not doing enough. Following the Soviet
            invasion of Afghanistan in December 1979, Carter withdrew from Senate consideration the
            unratified SALT II Treaty that he and Soviet General Secretary Leonid Brezhnev signed
            earlier that year. Meanwhile, nuclear attack false alarms in November 1979 and June 1980
            intensified preexisting White House concerns about U.S. command, control, and
            communications, and accentuated the prospect that a nuclear war could happen by
            accident. The volume includes documentation on the preparation of three subsequent
            Presidential Directives: PD–58, “Continuity of Government,” which President Carter
            signed on June 30, 1980; PD–59, “Nuclear Weapons Employment Policy,” which he signed on
            July 25, 1980; and PD-62, “Modifications in U.S. National Strategy,” which he signed on
            January 15, 1981.</tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>admin</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-06-30T11:15:03.283-04:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>hiteke</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2023-01-04T15:10:52.237-04:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>wicentowskijc</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-10-14T14:41:52.237-04:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
