<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76ve09p2">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume E–9, Part 2,
        Documents on the Middle East Region, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Documents on the Middle East Region, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume E–9, Part 2</title>
    <editor role="primary">Paul Hibbeln</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="epub"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2019</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2019</published-year>
    <published-date>2019-10-23</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">35</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">721</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This electronic-only volume is part of a
            subseries of volumes of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that
            documents the foreign policy decision making of the administrations of Presidents
            Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. This volume documents the formulation of U.S.
            policy toward the Middle East region as a whole, as well as the development of bilateral
            relationships with the countries of the Arabian Peninsula, from February 15, 1973, until
            December 28, 1976. During this period, Presidents Nixon and Ford and Secretary of State
            Henry A. Kissinger devoted much of their attention to managing the political, economic
            and strategic effects of the October 1973 Arab-Israeli war on U.S. interests in the
            region. Though the United States enjoyed cordial relations with every state on the
            Arabian Peninsula, with the exception of the People’s Democratic Republic of Yemen, the
            U.S. Government was criticized for its relationship with and assistance to Israel during
            the war. The 1973–1974 oil embargo, led by Arab members of the Organization of the
            Petroleum Exporting Countries against the United States and Western Europe, compounded
            the war’s impact and further complicated U.S. relations with most Middle Eastern states.
            In addition to raising international oil prices and creating a troubling financial
            situation for the United States, the embargo diminished U.S. prestige in the region at a
            moment when the Soviet Union’s influence in the eastern Mediterranean, the Horn of
            Africa, and South Asia appeared to be on the rise.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In response to this situation, the United
            States strengthened diplomatic relations with recently-independent Gulf states, who were
            responsive to offers of U.S. development expertise, technical assistance, and military
            aid. The Nixon and Ford administrations also courted Saudi Arabia as a political and
            economic partner, bolstered the modest U.S. military presence in the region, and
            expanded Washington’s diplomatic footprint with the establishment of new Embassies in
            the Gulf. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
