<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1958-60v16">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1958–1960, East Asia-Pacific
        Region; Cambodia; Laos, Volume XVI</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1958-60" type="sub-series">1958–1960</title>
    <title type="volume">East Asia-Pacific Region; Cambodia; Laos</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVI</title>
    <editor role="general">John P. Glennon</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">David W. Mabon</editor>
    <external-location loc="madison"
        >http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS195860v16</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1992</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>eisenhower</administration>
    <grouping administration="eisenhower">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1958</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1960</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">29</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1061</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume presents the record of U.S.
            policy toward Cambodia and Laos as well as as an overview of U.S. regional policy for
            East Asia during the Eisenhower administration.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">One principal emphasis of the compilation on
            the East Asia-Pacific region is the formulation of major regional policies at the
            highest level of the U.S. Government, as documented by the discussions and the policy
            papers of the National Security Council. Another major emphasis is the Southeast Asia
            Treaty Organization and the ANZUS Pact.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The focus for the Cambodia compilation is the
            friction between South Vietnam and Cambodia over border incidents and the attempt by the
            government of Ngo Dinh Diem to overthrow Cambodia’s leader, Prince Norodom Sihanouk. The
            assessments and recommendations of the U.S. missions in Saigon, Bangkok, and Phnom Penh
            were especially important in documenting these tensions. The focus shifts partly back to
            Washington in 1958 when the Eisenhower administration debated the issue of reducing U.S.
            assistance to Cambodia as a penalty for closer relations with the Sino-Soviet bloc. The
            Eisenhower administration handled a 1960 Cambodian request for jet aircraft and jet
            training of pilots at the interagency level under the auspices of the NSC, placing the
            focus of policy again in Washington at the interagency level.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Laos compilation comprises the greatest
            part of this volume, reflecting the fact that during the 1958–1960 period the Pathet Lao
            insurgency grew from a small conflict into the Eisenhower administration’s last major
            crisis in East Asia. The focus of the compilation alternates between Washington,
            Vientiane, and Bangkok. The volume begins with a visit to Washington by Lao Prime
            Minister Souvanna Phouma and concentrates on his discussions with high-ranking
            Eisenhower administration officials. In early summer 1958, the emphasis shifts to the
            elections in Laos for the supplemental seats in the National Assembly. The extent to
            which the United States was prepared to assist anti-communist candidates is documented
            in some detail. Until the so-called “emergency” in mid–1959, the compilation
            concentrates on events in Laos. With the threat to Laos from the Pathet Lao and possibly
            from North Vietnam, Washington policymakers considered some far-reaching alternatives in
            Laos. When the emergency receded in late 1959, the lack of coordination among U.S.
            Government agencies supporting different Lao anticommunist factions became more
            apparent.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
