<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v37">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXXVII, Energy
        Crisis, 1974–1980</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Energy Crisis, 1974–1980</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXXVII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Steven G. Galpern</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160895319</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2012</published-year>
    <published-date>2012-10-15</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1974</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">36</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">967</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a subseries of the
                <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that documents the most
            important foreign policy issues of the Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford presidential
            administrations. Because of the long-term nature of the 1970s energy crisis, however,
            this volume includes the period of the Jimmy Carter administration, covering U.S. policy
            from August 1974 until January 1981. The documentation in this volume focuses primarily
            on Ford and Carter policies aimed at mitigating the damage to the U.S. and global
            economy caused by rising oil prices imposed in 1973 by the OPEC cartel, and in 1978 by
            the perceived shortage of oil supplies resulting from the Iranian Revolution. The
            documents show that the United States conducted a broad-based multilateral diplomacy to
            address the crisis and that U.S. diplomats were active participants in the development
            of the International Energy Agency’s program of energy cooperation. The economic summits
            of the period brought together the heads of state from oil consuming industrialized
            countries in Rambouillet, London, Bonn, and Tokyo in an effort to devise a common
            strategy to deal with the impact of high oil prices on the global economy. This is one
            of a growing number of <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> volumes that
            document global issues instead of a bilateral relationship, reflecting the changing
            nature of U.S. foreign policy in response to an increasingly interrelated world. For
            documentation on the energy crisis prior to August 1974, see <tei:ref
                target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v36">
                <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi>, 1969–1976, volume XXXVI, Energy
                Crisis, 1969–1974</tei:ref>.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
