<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v27">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXVII, Mainland
        Southeast Asia; Regional Affairs</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Mainland Southeast Asia; Regional Affairs</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXVII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xxvii/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2000</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">41</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">946</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This compilation concentrates on the
            increasingly close and personal relations between President Johnson and the Prime
            Ministers of Australia and New Zealand. It also documents at the highest level the
            growing concern by Australia and New Zealand about the defense of Malaysia and Southeast
            Asia after the projected British withdrawal from East of Suez. There are no bilateral
            compilations for Australia and New Zealand, but the most important bilateral issues are
            raised in this compilation when President Johnson and Secretary of State Rusk met with
            the Australian and New Zealand Prime Ministers and Foreign Ministers. Some documentation
            on commercial relationships with these two countries is included in Foreign Relations,
            1964–1968, volumes VIII and IX. In addition, the compilation on Indonesia in Foreign
            Relations, 1964–1968, volume XXVI, contains documentation on Australian and New Zealand
            concern about the Indonesian confrontation with Malaysia. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The other regional compilation has two
            primary themes: the increasing inability of SEATO to respond to the war in Southeast
            Asia and the effort by the Johnson administration to foster economic development in
            Southeast Asia. In documenting U.S. concern with SEATO, the formal meetings have been
            treated in summary fashion. The economic development theme is presented primarily
            through the work of former World Bank President Eugene Black, President Johnson's
            Special Adviser on Southeast Asia. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The compilation on Burma focuses on Ne Win's
            visit to Washington in September 1966 and the Johnson administration's principal
            initiative to keep Burma non-aligned, independent, and at least partially engaged with
            the West. The Cambodia compilation documents a bilateral relationship that increasingly
            felt the strain of the expanding war in Southeast Asia. The steady deterioration of the
            U.S. relationship with Prince Sihanouk resulted in the May 1965 break in diplomatic
            relations. Another focus of the compilation is the growing concern in the U.S.
            Government about the Viet Cong use of Cambodian sanctuaries. The Cambodian Navy's
            capture of U.S. soldiers in 1968 provided a hostage negotiation situation that the
            Johnson administration feared might become another Pueblo crisis. The resolution of this
            issue is documented along with the periodic U.S. attempts to explore reestablishment of
            diplomatic relations with Cambodia. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The compilation on Thailand focuses on the
            collaboration between the United States and Thailand in the face of wars in Vietnam and
            Laos and hostility toward both countries from Cambodia. The compilation highlights the
            deliberations leading up to the decision not to send U.S. troops to Thailand (as was
            done in 1962), joint U.S.-Thailand military planning, cooperation in Laos, the U.S.
            interagency debate over the scope of U.S. military assistance to Thailand and the
            orientation of Thailand's armed forces, the need to combat potential insurgency in
            Thailand's northeast, Thailand's contribution to the war in Vietnam, and the stirrings
            of Thai political life in anticipation of elections in 1969. </tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>joewiz</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>joewiz</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>chalouma</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-08-30T11:00:50.667-05:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
