<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v18">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XVIII, Near
        East, 1962–1963</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Near East, 1962–1963</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Nina J. Noring</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xviii/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1995</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">66</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">881</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The primary focus of the documents in this
            volume is on the foreign policymaking process of the U.S. Government, including
            documentation illuminating policy formulation and major aspects and repercussions of its
            execution. Emphasis is placed on official memoranda that reveal policy positions, show
            differences within the U.S. Government over policy formulation, summarize developments
            and positions regarding an issue, contain intelligence or military assessments, and
            describe decisions or actions taken at the National Security Council. Some key
            instructions sent to diplomatic posts in the region are included when they demonstrate
            the details of the execution of foreign policy. Memoranda of conversations with foreign
            leaders both abroad and in Washington were selected to provide additional information on
            the origins and impact of foreign policy decisions.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The major topics and issues covered in volume
            XVIII are as follows: </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1. U.S. policy toward the conflict in Yemen
            and relations with the United Arab Republic and Saudi Arabia. The large amount of
            documentation on this subject in the volume reflects the extensive attention it received
            from the Kennedy administration. The material covered includes the U.S. response to the
            overthrow of the Yemeni monarchy and subsequent civil war in that country; background to
            the U.S. recognition of the Yemeni Republic in December 1962; U.S. efforts to mediate
            the conflict, including the mission of Ellsworth Bunker; and the dispatch of a U.S. air
            squadron to Saudi Arabia (Operation Hard Surface) in July 1963. The selection of
            documents reflects the regional nature of the Yemen conflict, with emphasis on U.S.
            relations with the United Arab Republic and Saudi Arabia, rather than on the situation
            in Yemen per se. The documents record how the U.S. initiative to improve relations with
            UAR President Gamal Abdul Nasser waned as the United States sought to assuage Saudi
            Arabia's concerns for its security. The volume concludes with growing U.S. Congressional
            opposition to the administration's program of economic assistance to the UAR. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">2. Israeli security issues and the Near East
            arms question. Emphasis is given to administration efforts to meet Israel's security
            concerns, including the decision in August 1962 to supply Israel with the Hawk missile,
            the first major weapon system provided to Israel by the United States. The volume
            records administration efforts to respond to Israel's request for a U.S. security
            guarantee and includes documentation on U.S.-Israeli military discussions in November
            1963. The volume also documents the U.S. desire to avert the introduction of advanced
            weapons in the region, President Kennedy's concern over Israel's nuclear program, and
            the mission of special Presidential emissary John J. McCloy to Cairo to discuss the
            possibility of mutual arms limitation by the UAR and Israel. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">3. Policies toward the Arab-Israeli dispute.
            Special coverage is given to U.S. support for the initiative to resolve the Palestinian
            refugee question (Joseph Johnson mission), and the initiative's demise. The volume also
            records the U.S. position on a number of Arab-Israeli issues, including incidents of
            violence, deliberations in the United Nations, the Jerusalem question, Israel's desire
            for direct negotiations with its Arab neighbors, and the growing importance of the Near
            East water question. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">4. U.S. policy toward Iran. This volume
            documents U.S. relations with Iran during the Shah's implementation of an extensive
            program of social and economic reforms which the Kennedy administration had urged him to
            undertake. It also records the U.S. response to the first signs of violent resistance to
            the Shah's regime from Iran's Islamic religious community. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">5. Other significant U.S. policies in the
            region. The volume also records U.S. support for the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan during
            a crisis that developed during the spring of 1963, the U.S. responses to coups d'etat in
            Syria and Iraq leading to changes in government, the U.S. reaction to inter-Arab unity
            talks in the spring of 1963, and U.S. concern over developments relating to the
            Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC). </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
