<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v21">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XXI,
        Africa</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Africa</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Nina Davis Howland</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/c15449.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1995</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">28</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">682</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation printed in this volume
            focuses on U.S. policy toward Africa, the formulation of U.S. policy, and on the most
            significant aspects of U.S. political, economic, and military relationships with African
            governments. Documents were selected that highlight policy discussions within the U.S.
            Government, with particular emphasis on the highest level at which policy on a
            particular subject was determined, that reveal policy positions and internal differences
            over policy, and that summarize developments or positions regarding an issue. The
            records of conversations with foreign leaders both abroad and in Washington that
            particularly illuminated U.S. relations with those countries were included. Space
            constraints precluded the inclusion of the substantial body of documentation from
            Embassies and from agencies in Washington on internal developments in African countries.
            Embassy reportage is limited to particularly significant cables that may have influenced
            the making of U.S. policy on the most critical issues. A number of relevant documents
            that conveyed finished intelligence on Africa to U.S. policymakers, in particular
            National Intelligence Estimates and Special National Intelligence Estimates, are
            included, but no effort was made to document the wider role of intelligence in the
            formulation or execution of policy. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The issues covered in the North African
            compilations include U.S. support for French President de Gaulle's announced program of
            self-determination for Algeria and U.S. relations with the newly-established Algerian
            government after July 1962. Material is included on U.S. economic and military
            assistance to Libya, Morocco, and Tunisia; the importance of the U.S. airbases and
            communications facilities in Libya and Morocco; and U.S. withdrawal from the Moroccan
            bases in December 1963. U.S. support for a negotiated settlement of the French-Tunisian
            clash over the French naval base at Bizerte is documented, as is U.S. support for
            peaceful settlement of the 1963 Algerian-Moroccan border conflict. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The compilations on Sub-Saharan Africa focus
            on expanding U.S. economic and military aid to the newly-independent nations of Africa
            and U.S. efforts to prevent the nations of the region from falling under Soviet
            domination. Documentation is included on U.S. policy concerns such as the U.S. decision
            to proceed with aid for Ghana's Volta River project, the strategic importance of the
            U.S. military base at Kagnew Station in Ethiopia, and U.S. efforts to find a modus
            vivendi between Ethiopia and Somalia. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Southern African compilations document
            U.S. support for peaceful transitions to stable, multi-racial societies in the
            white-ruled countries of Southern Africa. The documentation on Portuguese Africa shows
            the tension within U.S. policy, as the United States sought to balance its concern over
            Portugal's colonial policies in Angola and Mozambique against its desire to negotiate
            renewal of the Azores Base Agreement with its NATO ally, Portugal. The Rhodesian
            compilation documents U.S. support for British efforts to bring about full participation
            of the African populations of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland in the political
            process. The South African compilation deals with conclusion of a U.S. missile and
            satellite tracking station agreement with South Africa, and U.S. opposition to proposed
            mandatory U.N. economic sanctions against that country, as well as continuing U.S.
            opposition to the policy of apartheid and the unilateral U.S. embargo on arms shipments
            to South Africa announced in August 1963. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
