<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v15">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XV, Berlin
        Crisis, 1962–1963</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Berlin Crisis, 1962–1963</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Charles S. Sampson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xv/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1994</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">22</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">695</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In selecting documents for inclusion in
            volume XV, the editors recognized the predominant role of President Kennedy and his
            advisers at the White House in formulating policy with respect to Berlin and to the
            German question. This volume focuses on the many meetings of the President with his
            advisers from the White House, the Department of State, and other agencies, as well as
            the written advice to the President from these advisers. The editors have selected from
            White House, Department of State, and National Defense University records memoranda of
            conversation and records of meetings between the President and his principal foreign
            policy advisers. They have also included internal U.S. Government policy recommendations
            and decision papers relating to Berlin. The editors also included the advice and
            recommendations on foreign policy issues from top-level military commanders and
            advisers. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editors also focused on the principal
            aspects of the military contingency planning regarding Germany and the Berlin crisis
            that took place among the Western Allies as well as with representatives of the Soviet
            Union. Normal command and control activities of U.S. forces were not researched. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In focusing on the major lines of the
            development of the crisis, the editors have also presented a record of the U.S. reaction
            and response to the major political events within the Federal Republic of Germany
            insofar as they figured directly in ongoing high-level political negotiations. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Intelligence information regarding Soviet
            intentions with respect to Berlin and Germany in general was vitally important during
            the Berlin crisis and is reflected in the political documents selected for publication.
            The editors did not, however, attempt to document any particular operational activities
            by intelligence authorities in connection with the German problem or to explore the
            scope and impact of intelligence operations. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
