<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v25">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XXV,
        Organization of Foreign Policy; Information Policy; United Nations; Scientific
        Matters</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Organization of Foreign Policy; Information Policy; United Nations;
        Scientific Matters</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Paul Claussen</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Evan M. Duncan</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Jeffrey A. Soukup</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xxv/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2001</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">40</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1155</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editors of the volume sought to present
            documentation illuminating responsibility for major foreign policy decisions in the U.S.
            Government, with emphasis on the President and his advisers. The documents include
            memoranda and records of discussions that set forth policy issues and options and show
            decisions or actions taken. The emphasis is on the development of U.S. policy and on
            major aspects and repercussions of its execution rather than on the details of policy
            execution. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The first section of this volume deals with
            the organization and administration of foreign policy. Following the 1960 election,
            President-elect John F. Kennedy and his transition advisers focused on various proposals
            for modifying and streamlining the structure of the National Security Council apparatus.
            Documentation is presented on the interdepartmental review of foreign policy, the
            abolition of the Operations Coordinating Board, the use of Country Teams in the planning
            process, and enhanced involvement of the Vice President in national security affairs.
            This section also provides documentation on organizational changes in the Department of
            State, such as combining the positions of Counselor and Chairman of the Policy Planning
            Council, upgrading the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs and the Bureau of
            Intelligence and Research, abolishing 109 intra- and inter-departmental committees,
            closing marginal consular posts, improving the reporting system, and planning for the
            use of automation to expedite Department operations. Another part of this section covers
            the organization and administration of the Intelligence Community. The documents on
            information policy presented in the volume illustrate the U.S. Information Agency's
            initiatives in seeking to cooperate more closely with the State Department and other
            U.S. Government agencies, to present U.S. foreign policy objectives to the world in a
            positive manner, and to assess more accurately foreign opinion of the United States and
            its policies. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">President John F. Kennedy and his advisers
            took a keen interest in United Nations affairs. This volume includes documentation on
            the summer strategy sessions that discussed themes that the President would use when
            addressing the UN General Assembly. In the United Nations, U.S. policy shifted from
            supporting a "moratorium" on considering the question of Chinese representation to
            declaring it to be an "important question." Other major topics include the election of U
            Thant of Burma as Secretary-General after the death of Dag Hammarskjold, and the
            financing of UN operations in general and of peacekeeping operations in particular in
            view of Soviet opposition to paying for UN activities that it opposed. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Also presented are documents on Department of
            State involvement in the U.S. space program, U.S. cooperation with the Soviet Union in
            scientific research in outer space, support for UN resolutions concerning the peaceful
            uses of outer space, and the Department's role in the organization of space-based
            communications systems.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
