<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v06">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume VI,
        Kennedy-Khrushchev Exchanges</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Kennedy-Khrushchev Exchanges</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Charles S. Sampson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/volume_vi/volumevi.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1996</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">22</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">320</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Volume VI presents the complete
            correspondence between President Kennedy and Chairman Khrushchev. It is important for an
            understanding of this critical phase in U.S.-Soviet relations that this correspondence
            be collected and published in one volume rather than being dispersed through six or more
            volumes of this Foreign Relations subseries where particular issues considered by the
            leaders are relevant. The exchange of correspondence obviously had its own internal
            coherence as well as periodically addressing one or another of the ongoing crisis issues
            between the two nations documented fully elsewhere in the series. The collected
            correspondence offers in one volume a comprehensive overview of major Cold War problems
            and possibilities.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This correspondence includes both formal and
            public exchanges as well as the more informal and very confidential exchanges,
            transmitted through special emissaries, which became known as the "pen pal"
            correspondence. The channel was intended to give the two men a chance to exchange ideas
            in a "purely informal and personal way," as expressed by Chairman Khrushchev in his
            letter of September 29, 1961. Some of the informal messages were, however, made public
            immediately, sometimes before the recipient received them, but most of the messages were
            declassified only in later decades. The editors have indicated in the source footnotes
            if and when a communication was released to the public if that information was found.
        </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
