<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1958-60v15">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1958–1960, South and Southeast
        Asia, Volume XV</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1958-60" type="sub-series">1958–1960</title>
    <title type="volume">South and Southeast Asia</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Madeline Chi</editor>
    <editor role="primary">John P. Glennon</editor>
    <editor role="primary">William K. Klingaman</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Robert J. McMahon</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="madison"
        >http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS195860v15</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1992</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>eisenhower</administration>
    <grouping administration="eisenhower">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1958</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1960</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">27</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1205</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume presents documentation on U.S.
            relations with and policies toward the nations of South Asia (Afghanistan, Pakistan,
            India, Nepal, and Sri Lanka [then Ceylon]) as well as with the Southeast Asian nations
            of Thailand and the Philippines.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume includes Department of State
            memoranda of the conversations between Secretaries of State John Foster Dulles and
            Christian A. Herter and their counterparts in the South Asian and South-east Asian
            nations and internal U.S. Government policy recommendations and decision papers relating
            to such important initiatives as: the U.S. “package plan” for resolution of the most
            serious issues between India and Pakistan; formulation and execution of the U.S.
            Government policy of furnishing the maximum possible economic aid to India;
            stabilization of the U.S. alliance relationship with Pakistan; consultation between U.S.
            officials and officers of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development
            regarding loans to the countries in the South Asia region; development of policy
            measures designed to limit Soviet influence in Afghanistan and promote better relations
            between Afghanistan and Pakistan; and efforts to solve issues related to the
            U.S.-Philippine Military Bases Agreement.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Telegrams document the important policy
            recommendations of U.S. representatives in the area, especially the influential U.S.
            Ambassadors in India, Pakistan, the Philippines and Thailand. Embassy files were of
            special use in the compilations on Thailand and the Philippines. The volume also
            includes policy recommendations of the Joint Chiefs of Staff regarding various major
            foreign affairs policies as well as key National Intelligence Estimates and Special
            National Intelligence Estimates related to South and Southeast Asia.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
