<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v02">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume II,
        Organization and Management of U.S. Foreign Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Organization and Management of U.S. Foreign Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume II</title>
    <editor role="primary">David C. Humphrey</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/ii/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2006</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">29</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">878</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The focus of this volume is the organization
            and management of the foreign policy process. This theme runs throughout the volume, but
            is most clearly evident in the first chapter, “The NSC System.” This chapter documents
            the Nixon administration’s foreign policy process as it was conceived by President
            Nixon, his Special Assistant Henry Kissinger, and other key advisers. The chapter shows
            how the foreign policy decision making process was supposed to work in theory, and then
            documents how the system worked in reality. A primary concern of Nixon and Kissinger was
            that the President retain control over the foreign policy process through his National
            Security Council (NSC) Staff, and that the White House oversee the implementation of
            presidential decisions. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As the documents indicate, the Nixon
            administration believed that it was fighting an ongoing battle to retain Presidential
            and White House control of the foreign policy decision making process against the
            bureaucratic forces of the Departments of State and Defense. The first chapter of this
            volume documents how this struggle for control caused friction between the White House
            and the Departments of State and Defense, as well as a certain amount of personal
            rivalry and tension between Kissinger, Secretary of State William Rogers, and Secretary
            of Defense Melvin Laird.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The second chapter of the volume focuses on
            the related issue of reorganization and revitalization of the Intelligence Community.
            This reform was driven by President Nixon’s and the White House Staff’s view that they
            were not getting the right intelligence and that the United States was spending too much
            on intelligence for the product it was receiving. In addition, Nixon and the White House
            were concerned that covert operations, which they believed had a tendency to go on
            indefinitely, were not properly supportive of larger U.S. foreign policy objectives.
            Finally, the second chapter documents a formal reorganization of the intelligence
            function at the Department of Defense, where it was widely held that the intelligence
            function was too diffuse and not properly coordinated. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The third chapter deals with the
            administration and management of the Department of State by the Department’s principal
            officers and by President Nixon and the White House. The documents indicate that the
            President was determined to appoint his own people to key positions in the Department
            and ambassadorships, but he also wished to push forward younger Foreign Service officers
            to ambassadorial posts. Because of balance of payment problems, Nixon was also
            determined to cut overseas personnel, which would naturally affect Department of State
            overseas operations. The President also wished to upgrade the Department’s Latin
            American Bureau, but needed Congressional approval. This chapter deals with the question
            of the loyalty of the Foreign Service officers to the President, the role—or, more
            accurately, the lack of a role—for professional women in the Department of State and
            foreign affairs bureaucracy, and the question of Foreign Service spouses (then called
            wives, since the Foreign Service consisted overwhelmingly of men).</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
