<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1981-88v03">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1981–1988, Volume III, Soviet
        Union, January 1981–January 1983</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1981-88" type="sub-series">1981–1988</title>
    <title type="volume">Soviet Union, January 1981–January 1983</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume III</title>
    <editor role="primary">James Graham Wilson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-093227-4</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2016</published-year>
    <published-date>2016-03-16</published-date>
    <administration>reagan</administration>
    <grouping administration="reagan">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1980</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1983</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">30</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">896</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is the first of four Soviet
            bilateral volumes in the Reagan subseries. This volume commences with Ronald Reagan’s
            election on November 4, 1980, and concludes with his approval of National Security
            Decision Directive 75, “U.S. Relations With the USSR,” on January 17, 1983, which
            stated: “U.S. policy toward the Soviet Union will consist of three elements: external
            resistance to Soviet imperialism; internal pressure on the USSR to weaken the sources of
            Soviet imperialism; and negotiations to eliminate, on the basis of strict reciprocity,
            outstanding disagreements.”</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Cold War flashpoints and disputes during this
            period included: the Soviet occupation of Afghanistan; the potential Soviet invasion of
            Poland; the possibility that the Reagan administration would act to delay Soviet
            construction of a Siberian gas pipeline to Western Europe; the execution of NATO’s 1979
            “Dual Track Decision”; the implementation of a strategic modernization program on the
            part of the United States; and Soviet meddling in Central America and the Middle East.
            Additionally, three cases of Soviet human rights abuses drew and sustained President
            Reagan’s personal attention: Anatoly Shcharanskiy, Andrei Sakharov, and a group of
            Siberian Pentecostals living in the basement of the U.S. Embassy in Moscow.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
