<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v19">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XIX, South
        Asia</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">South Asia</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XIX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Seth A. Rotramel</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160951565</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2019</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2019</published-year>
    <published-date>2019-08-08</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">45</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1104</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the Carter
            administration’s approach to the South Asia region in response to the shifting political
            landscape at the end of the 1970s. During the first three years of Carter’s presidency,
            U.S. relations with South Asia were shaped by three contextual factors: tensions over
            nuclear proliferation, the rivalry between India and Pakistan, and the Carter
            administration’s preference for developing closer ties with democratically-elected
            governments. Under this preference, U.S. relations with India improved while relations
            with Pakistan withered. The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in late December 1979 led
            Carter to seek closer relations with Pakistan in order to thwart what his administration
            feared to be a new era of Soviet expansion. Carter’s efforts to enlist support against
            the Soviet Union regarding Afghanistan eclipsed the administration’s fear of nuclear
            proliferation, and U.S. sponsorship of India-Pakistan rapprochement suffered from the
            U.S. attempt to send Pakistan large scale military aid and Prime Minister Indira
            Gandhi’s refusal to condemn the Soviet invasion. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume also includes documentation on the
            Carter administration’s policy towards Bangladesh, Sri Lanka, and Nepal. While issues
            such as the attempted coup d’état in Bangladesh in 1977 and Bangladesh’s membership in
            the United Nations Security Council during the Iranian hostage crisis brought Bangladesh
            in conflict with the Carter administration, relations toward these countries were
            largely subject to policy objectives relating to India and Pakistan. The promotion of
            democratic governance and human rights, along with food aid, represented the significant
            policy initiatives towards these countries. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
