<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76ve14p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume E–14, Part 1,
        Documents on the United Nations, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Documents on the United Nations, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume E–14, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">William B. McAllister</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="epub"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2008</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">607</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the foreign policy of
            the Nixon and Ford administrations concerning issues that were primarily negotiated in
            United Nations bodies, other international governmental organizations, and
            non-governmental organizations. The topics covered in this volume are related to the
            chapters in <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi>, 1969–1976, Volume E–2,
            Documents on Global Issues 1973–1976. In both volumes, the issues addressed crossed
            “traditional” bilateral and regional boundaries, often dealt with topics not previously
            given to sustained, high-level negotiations, and frequently required novel approaches,
            integrated thinking, and revision of bureaucratic organizations. The table of contents
            provides the best idea of the kinds of issues documented by this volume: population
            policy, food policy, women’s issues, general United Nation affairs, and controversies
            surrounding United Nations membership. This is by no means a complete list of the global
            issues and United Nations topics that the Nixon and Ford administrations confronted.
            Others, such as energy, disarmament, transnational economic issues, and refugee policy,
            are covered in separate volumes in the 1969–1976 subseries. It is the opinion of the
            editor that this volume covers the era most faithfully by focusing on those topics that
            the Nixon and Ford administrations recognized as distinctly global issues dealt with on
            a transnational basis, primarily through the United Nations. Topics treated primarily on
            a bilateral or regional basis can be found in other volumes in this subseries.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
