<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v23">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXIII,
        Arab-Israeli Dispute, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Arab-Israeli Dispute, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIII</title>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Steven G. Galpern</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160928475</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2015</published-year>
    <published-date>2015-08-17</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1972</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">32</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1123</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As part of a subseries of volumes of the
                <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that documents the most
            important issues in the foreign policy of the administrations of Richard M. Nixon and
            Gerald R. Ford, this volume documents U.S. policy toward the Arab-Israeli Dispute
            between January 1969 and December 1972. During his first term in office, President
            Richard Nixon was confronted with the challenges posed by the outcomes of the June 1967
            Arab-Israeli War, most notably Israel’s acquisition of territory from its Arab neighbors
            in the Sinai Peninsula, the Gaza Strip, the Golan Heights, and the West Bank; lingering
            hostilities between Israeli and Arab forces; the rise of the Palestine Liberation
            Organization under the leadership of Yasser Arafat; and growing Soviet influence in the
            Arab states. Although this volume primarily traces the administration’s efforts to
            broker an Egyptian-Israeli peace settlement while seeking to preserve a precarious
            regional balance of power between the belligerents, it also covers other aspects of U.S.
            bilateral relations with Egypt, Israel, Jordan, Lebanon, and Syria, including nuclear
            matters and arms sales. Among the salient themes highlighted in the volume include the
            impact of the shifting bureaucratic balance of power within the Nixon administration’s
            foreign policy apparatus, from the Department of State to the White House, on the making
            of policy toward the Arab-Israeli dispute, as well as the influence of the Cold War
            conflict upon U.S. perceptions of the strategic situation in the Middle East and the
            prospects for peace.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
