<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v17">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XVII, Eastern
        Europe</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Eastern Europe</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVII</title>
    <editor role="primary">James E. Miller</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xvii/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1996</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">28</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">579</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation in this volume highlights
            U.S. policy toward Eastern Europe, particularly the U.S. response to the crisis created
            by the August 1968 Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia. Prior to the invasion, U.S. policy
            in the region had been characterized by an ongoing effort to loosen ties between the
            Soviet Union and its Communist satellites through the use of limited economic
            assistance. This policy of "Bridge Building" to Eastern Europe through selective use of
            U.S. economic power was only partially successful. President Johnson faced serious
            opposition from within Congress to this initiative. In addition, Eastern European
            Communist regimes, while eager to obtain U.S. aid, wanted few conditions attached to its
            utilization and aimed to use outside assist-ance to consolidate their political control.
            The rise of a Communist reform movement in Czechoslovakia, while welcomed by the United
            States, offered U.S. diplomacy little practical assistance in carrying out this policy.
            The Communist reformers were fundamentally hostile to the United States. As a result the
            Johnson administration was an interested observer as the Czech and Soviet states
            confronted each other. After the Soviet invasion of August 1968, the United States
            feared further Soviet military moves and actively sought to provide support to bolster
            the independence of Austria, Yugoslavia, Romania, and Finland. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
