<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v24">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXIV, Middle
        East Region and Arabian Peninsula, 1969–1972; Jordan, September 1970</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Middle East Region and Arabian Peninsula, 1969–1972; Jordan, September
        1970</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Linda W. Qaimmaqami</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/xxiv/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2008</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1972</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">32</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">966</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editors of this volume sought to present
            documentation that explains and illuminates the major foreign policy decisions of the
            President on the Middle East region, the Persian Gulf, and the Arabian Peninsula and
            Jordan, and represents the counsel of his key foreign policy advisers. The volume
            focuses on U.S. regional policy in the Middle East and the Indian Ocean. It also has
            chapters on U.S. bilateral relations with Saudi Arabia, Yemen, the smaller Persian Gulf
            states, and on the Jordan crisis of September 1970. The documents used in the Middle
            East regional part of the volume include memoranda, records of discussions, cables, and
            papers that set forth policy issues and options and show decisions or actions taken. The
            Jordan crisis section of the volume uses similar documentation and also relies heavily
            on transcripts of crucial telephone conversations.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tei:hi rend="italic">Middle East Region</tei:hi>. President Nixon relied upon his two
            principal foreign policy advisers, Secretary of State William Rogers and Assistant for
            National Security Affairs Henry Kissinger, for major foreign policy initiatives toward
            the region. Other high-level officials, such as Secretary of Defense Melvin Laird and
            Director of Central Intelligence Richard Helms, provided additional counsel. Because the
            editors’ primary focus was on the policy process—recommendations, discussions, and then
            final decisions—the focus of the volume is largely on events in Washington; however, it
            also covers events and developments in the Middle East region and the Indian Ocean as
            they affected the policy process.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The themes of this section are framed by the
            Nixon administration’s efforts to replace the political and military structure left by
            the former British Empire with a newer structure that met America’s cold war needs. As
            the United States worked with the British to restructure the region militarily and
            politically, this required diplomatic contact with Saudi Arabia, Iran, and the various
            sheikdoms that eventually made up the United Arab Emirates, as well as Qatar and
            Bahrain. Other themes emerged after Britain’s political and military departure from the
            region, including the Nixon administration’s efforts to articulate a grand strategy
            toward the Middle East region through arms sales and military modernization for its
            regional allies, enlarging the U.S. naval presence in the Indian Ocean through
            negotiations with the British over Diego Garcia, and preventing Ceyelonese and Soviet
            efforts to demilitarize the Indian Ocean. Additional themes include competition between
            Kissinger and Rogers for dominance in policymaking and the reluctance of Nixon and
            Kissinger to be involved in regional issues, unless the Shah of Iran or King Faisal of
            Saudi Arabia demanded their personal attention.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <tei:hi rend="italic">The Jordan Crisis</tei:hi>. This chapter documents the September
            1970 crisis in Jordan. This crisis confronted the Nixon administration with the
            possibility that the monarchy of King Hussein, a major U.S. ally in the Middle East,
            would not survive. Although conflict existed between King Hussein and the Palestine
            Liberation Organization (PLO) during the months preceding and following September 1970,
            this chapter focuses on the key 4-week period that defined the most intense phase of the
            conflict. It opens with the hijacking of four commercial airliners by the Popular Front
            for the Liberation of Palestine. These hijackings led to intense fighting between the
            PLO and the Jordanian Arab Army, and the chapter emphasizes Nixon and Kissinger’s close
            involvement in the day-to-day developments and the final resolution of the
            crisis.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
