<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v17">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XVII, Near
        East, 1961–1962</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Near East, 1961–1962</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Nina J. Noring</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xvii/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1994</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">59</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">790</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The primary focus of the documents in this
            volume is on the foreign policymaking process of the U.S. Government, including
            documentation illuminating policy formulation and major aspects and repercussions of its
            execution. Emphasis is placed on official memoranda that reveal policy positions, show
            differences within the U.S. Government over policy formulation, summarize developments
            and positions regarding an issue, contain intelligence or military assessments, and
            describe decisions or actions taken at the National Security Council. Some key
            instructions sent to diplomatic posts in the region are included when they demonstrate
            the details of the execution of foreign policy. Memoranda of conversations with foreign
            leaders both abroad and in Washington were selected to provide additional information on
            the origins and impact of foreign policy decisions. The major topics and issues covered
            in volume XVII are as follows: </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1. Interagency review of U.S. policy toward
            Iran and the U.S. decision to support a program of reform in that country. This topic
            received the greatest amount of coverage in the volume because of the extensive
            attention given to it by the highest levels of the U.S. Government and because the
            decision to support a program of economic and social, but not political, reform and to
            throw complete U.S. support behind Iranian Prime Minister Ali Amini had important
            ramifications for subsequent U.S.-Iranian relations. Records of discussions with the
            Shah, especially during his June 1964 visit to the United States, are included. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Additional documentation dealing with the
            interagency review and containing additional details relating to U.S. economic and
            military assistance programs in Iran is included in the compilation on Iran in <tei:ref
                target="frus1961-63v17-21mSupp">the microfiche supplement</tei:ref>. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">2. Policies toward and efforts to resolve the
            Arab-Israeli dispute. Documentation is included describing U.S. policies and positions
            toward the numerous issues of the Arab-Israeli dispute. The most extensive coverage is
            given to U.S. support for and involvement in an initiative to resolve the Palestinian
            refugee question conducted by Joseph Johnson, who was a special representative of the
            U.N. Palestine Conciliation Commission. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Other issues include incidents of violence
            and violations of the 1949 Armistice Agreements, the Jerusalem question, Arab-Israeli
            differences over distribution of the waters of the Jordan River, matters relating to
            refugees and to Palestinian political organization, the Arab boycott of Israel, the
            question of direct negotiations between Israel and the Arab states, Arab treatment of
            non-Israeli Jews, location of foreign Embassies in Israel, and Israeli border questions.
            Documentation concerning U.N. General Assembly and Security Council consideration of
            Arab-Israeli issues and on interactions between U.S. domestic politics and U.S.
            Arab-Israeli policies is also included. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">3. U.S. efforts to improve U.S. relations
            with President Nasser of the United Arab Republic. An important focus of the volume is
            the policy discussion and debate within the U.S. Government concerning the possibility
            of improving U.S. relations with Nasser. This policy review addressed questions of U.S.
            economic assistance to the United Arab Republic and whether to invite Nasser on a State
            visit to Washington. U.S. policy concerning economic assistance to the United Arab
            Republic is a major subject, but specific economic assistance programs are not covered
            in detail. The volume includes reports of conversations between U.S. officials and
            Nasser, important intelligence assessments concerning Nasser and his country, records of
            the most important correspondence between Presidents Kennedy and Nasser, and material
            showing the interest of key White House aides in improving relations with Nasser and
            President Kennedy's views on this subject, as well as some reporting on political
            developments within the country and on Nasser's relations with other Arab countries and
            Iran. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">4. Israeli security issues. Among the most
            important issues covered in the volume is the background to the U.S. decision in August
            1962 to supply Israel with the Hawk missile, the first major weapon system provided to
            Israel by the United States. Another issue documented in the volume is U.S. concern over
            Israel's nuclear reactor at Dimona. Little coverage is given in this volume to U.S.
            economic assistance to Israel or to political developments within Israel, although some
            additional documentation on these topics is included in <tei:ref
                target="frus1961-63v17-21mSupp">the microfiche supplement</tei:ref>. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">5. The withdrawal of Syria from the United
            Arab Republic. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. officials were concerned that Syria's
            withdrawal from its union with Egypt in September 1961 might lead to a general Near East
            war with disastrous ramifications for U.S. interests. The editor has selected
            substantial documentation on the U.S. response to this event, primarily handled through
            diplomatic channels, including the available White House documentation. Special
            attention was also given to the formulation of U.S. policy toward the new Syrian
            Government. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">6. The Kuwait crisis of 1961. The editor has
            included documentation on the reaction of the United States during the brief crisis that
            developed when Iraq reasserted claims to Kuwait at the time of Kuwait's independence
            from the United Kingdom. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
