<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v32">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXXII,
        Dominican Republic; Cuba; Haiti; Guyana</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Dominican Republic; Cuba; Haiti; Guyana</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXXII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Daniel L. Lawler</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Carolyn Yee</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/johnsonlb/xxxii/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2005</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">35</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">992</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents U.S. policy toward the
            Dominican Republic including a period of great crisis that culminated in the decision to
            send U.S. military forces to that country. The United States then oversaw a
            reconstitution of the Dominican Government and a Dominican presidential election in
            1967. Also covered is U.S. policy toward Cuba, essentially an account of U.S. attempts
            to isolate Castro’s Cuba both diplomatically and economically through sanctions, and the
            internal Washington debate over the extent and nature of U.S. covert policy toward the
            island nation. The remainder of the volume does not cover a broad swath of countries,
            but concentrates on the two most difficult relationships in the area for the United
            States: Haiti and the British Colony of British Guiana (after 1966, independent Guyana).
            Lyndon B. Johnson made the major foreign policy decisions during his presidency, and the
            editors sought to document his role as far as possible. In the case of the intervention
            in the Dominican Republic, Johnson relied heavily upon the recommendations of his key
            advisers and special envoys, and their role and advice to the President is documented.
            It will become obvious that during the Dominican crisis— especially through the
            transcripts of Presidential tapes—Johnson was a hands-on President who after assessing
            advice, made the major IV Preface policy decisions. The role of the President and his
            major foreign policy advisers, including his hard-to-document Secretary of State, Dean
            Rusk, are less pronounced in the other chapters in the volume dealing with Cuba, Haiti,
            and British Guiana/Guyana. This volume follows the pattern of other volumes in the
            1964–1968 subseries: focusing on policy formulation in Washington. In the case of the
            Dominican Republic there is a close connection between events in Santo Domingo and
            policy in Washington. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
