<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v29">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXIX, Eastern
        Europe; Eastern Mediterranean, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Eastern Europe; Eastern Mediterranean, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIX</title>
    <editor role="primary">James E. Miller</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Douglas E. Selvage</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Laurie Van Hook</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/xxix/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2008</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">29</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">873</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The coverage of this volume is split almost
            equally between Eastern Europe and the Eastern Mediterranean. The Eastern Europe section
            begins with a general chapter that covers the entire Soviet bloc region and deals almost
            exclusively with U.S. efforts to liberalize and expand trade with Eastern Europe. The
            second chapter is also a general one. It deals with U.S. Government policy and the
            bureaucratic debate about—and ultimately, the decision on how to fund—Radio Free Europe
            (the U.S.-directed—and clandestinely funded—broadcasting service aimed at Eastern
            Europe), and Radio Liberty (a similar service aimed at the Soviet Union). The remainder
            of the Eastern Europe section of the volume comprises eight chapters on U.S. bilateral
            relations with Soviet bloc Eastern European countries, as well as with Austria and
            Finland.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The countries covered in the three chapters
            on the Eastern Mediterranean generally have a much higher profile than the countries
            covered in the chapters on Eastern Europe, and indicate a strong Presidential and White
            House interest in events and policies there. This is particularly true for Greece. The
            Cyprus chapter is a continuation of the Foreign Relations series’ longstanding coverage
            of the ongoing dispute on that island between Greek and Turkish Cypriots, which was
            overlaid with tensions between the governments in Athens and Ankara. The final chapter
            of the volume is primarily about U.S. efforts to discourage Turkish narcotics
            production.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
