<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v11p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XI, Part 1,
        Iran: Hostage Crisis, November 1979–September 1980</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Iran: Hostage Crisis, November 1979–September 1980</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XI, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">Linda W. Qaimmaqami</editor>
    <editor role="general">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2020</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2020</published-year>
    <published-date>2020-11-17</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1979</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1981</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">48</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">941</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the foreign policy
            decisions of the administration of President Jimmy Carter. The volume documents the
            Carter administration’s efforts to resolve the U.S.-Iranian crisis over the taking of
            U.S. hostages in Tehran. The absence of direct diplomatic communications between the
            United States and Iran during this period compelled the Carter administration to rely on
            a variety of official and unofficial intermediaries in its attempts to negotiate the
            release of the hostages. The administration considered and pursued a variety of
            diplomatic and economic strategies intended to convince the Iranian Government that it
            should take steps to end the crisis and secure the return of the hostages. Such moves
            included negotiations regarding the former Shah of Iran and his presence in the United
            States and other countries. The volume also documents Carter administration officials’
            consideration of military pressure strategies, while they concurrently developed
            operational plans to rescue the hostages. Lack of success in the negotiation efforts led
            President Carter to authorize a military rescue mission in April 1980. The volume
            documents the rescue operation’s failure to free the hostages, as well as the Carter
            team’s handling of the mission aftermath and their continued work to achieve a
            resolution to the hostage crisis. The volume concludes in early September 1980, when
            Iran seated a new government and several leading Iranian officials publicly suggested
            their readiness to end the hostage crisis.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
