<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v24">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XXIV, Laos
        Crisis</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Laos Crisis</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/e13/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1994</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">23</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1095</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editors included in this volume documents
            indicating the advice and recommendations on foreign policy issues from top-level
            military commanders and advisers. The editors also focused on the high-level discussion
            of military contingency planning regarding Laos. The Kennedy administration produced an
            inordinate amount of contingency plans for Laos, most of which were never implemented.
            The emphasis in this volume, however, is on the high-level consideration of contingency
            planning, rather than on the mechanics and details of the actual plans. Normal command
            and control activities of U.S. forces were not researched. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In focusing on the major lines of the
            development of the crisis, the editors have also presented a record of the U.S. reaction
            and response to the major political events within Laos since they figured directly in
            the formulation of policy and the political negotiations at the Geneva Conference. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Intelligence information regarding Pathet
            Lao, North Vietnamese, Chinese, and Soviet political and strategic intentions with
            respect to Laos is reflected in documents selected for publication here. The editors did
            not, however, attempt to document the operational activities by intelligence authorities
            in connection with Laos. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
