<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1917-72PubDipv07">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1917–1972, Volume VII, Public
        Diplomacy, 1964–1968</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1917-72-public-diplomacy-retrospective" type="sub-series">1917–1972</title>
    <title type="volume">Public Diplomacy, 1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VII</title>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Charles V. Hawley</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2018</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2018</published-year>
    <published-date>2018-12-07</published-date>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">retrospective</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">40</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">622</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the efforts of the
            Lyndon B. Johnson administration to craft public diplomacy and information policy during
            the middle period of the Cold War. A major emphasis is on the various ways the United
            States Information Agency (USIA) presented U.S. foreign policy objectives to global
            audiences during a time of great social upheaval within the United States, particularly
            during the Civil Rights movement. It also describes how the Johnson administration
            ensured both USIA and the Department of State utilized a variety of public diplomacy
            tools in the face of numerous crises that defined the 1960s. These crises included the
            assassination of John F. Kennedy and transition to the Johnson administration, the
            Dominican Republic intervention, the ongoing nuclear test-ban treaty negotiations, the
            Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia, and, most significant, the Vietnam war, which was a
            dominant focus through Johnson’s presidency. Additional documentation chronicles the
            Johnson administration’s attempts to reassure the world of U.S. stability following
            Kennedy’s death, to promote a domestic policy during a period of tumult and great
            cultural change, and to advance the Department of State’s educational exchange
            activities, particularly with the Soviet Union and the developing world. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"/>
    </summary>
</volume>
