<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v08" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume VIII, Vietnam,
        January–October 1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, January–October 1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">John M. Carland</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160794292</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2010</published-year>
    <published-date>2010-06-24</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1972</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1972</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">43</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1100</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p>The Easter Offensive, and its ramifications, represents the most significant event in
            Indochina for U.S. policy in this period, and documentary coverage of the event
            dominates the volume, concentrating mainly on what happened in North and South Vietnam,
            policy formulation and decision making in Washington, and the negotiations in Paris.
            Only a very small number of documents relate to events and policy in Laos and Cambodia,
            and then only as they relate to events and policy in Vietnam.</tei:p>
        <tei:p>Documents in this volume examine the link between force and diplomacy in U.S.
            national security policy toward the Vietnam war. In the period the volume covers, force
            drove diplomacy. Only by recognizing this can the process by which America’s Vietnam war
            policy was formulated and implemented be fully understood. Controlling the process was a
            small circle of men, led by President Richard M. Nixon, and which included the
            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs, Henry A. Kissinger; the President’s
            Deputy Assistant for National Security Affairs, Major General Alexander M. Haig; and a
            few National Security Council officials trusted by Kissinger.</tei:p>
        <tei:p>Sources for this volume include messages and memoranda that illuminate the
            decision-making process in a bureaucracy. They can be found in Nixon’s papers, in
            Kissinger’s papers, in military and diplomatic records in the National Archives, and in
            other repositories. Transcripts of Nixon’s taped conversations with senior policy
            advisers, as well as a collection of transcripts of Kissinger’s telephone conversations,
            provide an additional level of detail. A third collection, less well known than the
            other two but almost as significant, is that of Admiral Thomas Moorer, Chairman of the
            Joint Chiefs of Staff, and includes diary excerpts and telephone conversations. This
            volume, therefore, documents the implementation of U.S. policy toward Vietnam during the
            Easter Offensive more thoroughly than ever before.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
