<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v05">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume V, Vietnam,
        1967</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, 1967</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume V</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kent Sieg</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/johnsonlb/v/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2002</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">39</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1175</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume covers a broad range of topics and
            themes, the foremost of which is the U.S. effort to explore a possible negotiated
            settlement of the war. There is in-depth coverage of the major unsuccessful peace
            initiatives, Sunflower and Pennsylvania to the North Vietnamese and Buttercup to the
            National Liberation Front, as well as less detailed coverage of other peace initiatives
            thought at the time by U.S. policymakers to be less promising. Another major theme of
            the volume is the military intensification of the war effort to force the enemy to
            accept a peace settlement. The Presidential decisions to intensify the bombing campaign
            against North Vietnam and the long debate and final compromise decision by Johnson to
            augment the level of U.S. forces in Vietnam are part of this theme. The problem of U.S.
            domestic support for the war is another theme, as the Johnson administration grappled
            with building anti-war pressure. During the period covered by the volume, the Johnson
            administration named a new Ambassador to Vietnam, Ellsworth Bunker, put Robert Komer in
            charge of pacification and rural development, and then engaged in an effort to encourage
            reorganization and reform of the South Vietnam Government. This campaign, which had
            mixed results, is another main theme. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Documents in the volume also cover the South
            Vietnamese presidential elections, especially U.S. concerns about lack of unity between
            the two military contenders for the presidency. Another focus is the debate within the
            U.S. intelligence community over the size of the enemy in South Vietnam, the so-called
            "order of battle" controversy. During 1967 the administration conducted a reassessment
            of the war, a continuing theme of U.S. Vietnam policy, which resulted in advice to the
            President to stay the course. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
