<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v09">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume IX, Vietnam,
        October 1972–January 1973</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, October 1972–January 1973</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume IX</title>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">John M. Carland</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160829994</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2010</published-year>
    <published-date>2010-09-16</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1972</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1973</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">41</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1200</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the marathon four-day
            negotiating session between Kissinger and North Vietnamese representative Le Duc Tho in
            Paris (October 8-11, 1972). The peace agreement they reached was rejected by South
            Vietnamese President Nguyen Van Thieu. The United States attempted to convince Thieu
            that he was wrong, and in November Nixon sent Kissinger back to Paris to renegotiate 69
            points on behalf of the South Vietnamese. The North Vietnamese, fiercely disagreeing
            with the U.S. move, decided that they too would renegotiate issues previously agreed to.
            By mid-November, the talks were on the verge of collapse. Consequently, the central
            goals of U.S. foreign policy over the next few weeks were to compel both South Vietnam
            and North Vietnam to accept, in its main tenets, the agreement that the United States
            had negotiated with the latter in October.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the wake of unproductive December
            meetings, Nixon took one of his most controversial decisions: re-mining Haiphong Harbor
            and ordering an air campaign against the Hanoi-Haiphong complex. Nixon hoped to shock
            the North Vietnamese back to negotiations and remind the South Vietnamese that America’s
            commitment to the defense and survival of South Vietnam was contingent upon South
            Vietnam supporting the agreement. North Vietnam agreed to return to the negotiating
            table, and Thieu agreed to the new terms. In early January 1973, Kissinger and Le Duc
            Tho returned to Paris and in several days of hard bargaining ironed out the last details
            of the settlement. Titled the “Agreement on Ending the War and Restoring Peace in
            Vietnam,” the accords included a number of minor compromises negotiated in November,
            December, and January. In its essentials, however, it remained remarkably similar to the
            document that Kissinger and Le Duc Tho had agreed to in October.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
