<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v24">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XXIV, South
        America; Latin America Region</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">South America; Latin America Region</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Sara Berndt</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2018</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2018</published-year>
    <published-date>2018-12-18</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">41</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1085</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Department of State released today a
            portion of <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</tei:hi>,
            1977‒1980, Volume XXIV, South America; Latin America Region. Two compilations in this
            volume, on Argentina and the Latin America Region, were previously released in October
            2017 as part of the Argentina Declassification Project. Today’s publication completes
            the volume with compilations on nine more South American countries.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a subseries of volumes
            in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that documents the
            foreign policy of the Carter administration. The Carter administration’s human rights
            policy made both a broad and unpredictable impact on U.S. relations with South American
            nations. In Ecuador, the policy led the United States to press for the first free
            elections in 6 years, which were held successfully. The same focus on Bolivia, however,
            could not stave off a period of political instability that saw four coups in just over
            two years, including the notorious “cocaine coup” in July 1980. Administration
            perceptions of the different degrees to which countries’ were willing to reform their
            human rights practices led to a cooling toward Paraguay and a warming toward Uruguay.
            The ongoing investigation into the assassinations of former Chilean Foreign Minister
            Orlando Letelier and U.S. citizen Ronni Moffitt in Washington in 1976 also led to a deep
            chill in U.S. relations with Chile.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Compilations regarding U.S. policy toward a
            number of other countries focus on other issues. In Venezuela, the administration
            enjoyed a close working relationship with President Carlos Andres Perez, encompassed by
            the ongoing investigations into the Cubana Airlines bombing and Letelier assassination.
            Only occasional high-level attention was paid to Colombia, most notably during a hostage
            crisis involving U.S. Ambassador Diego Asencio. The compilation on Peru focuses on U.S.
            relations with its leftist military junta, dealing with the Peruvian economic crisis,
            and eventual elections. U.S. relations with Brazil were generally cool during the Carter
            administration, with disputes over non-proliferation, trade, and human rights at the
            forefront of bilateral problems.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
