<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v06">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume VI, Vietnam,
        January–August 1968</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, January–August 1968</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kent Sieg</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/johnsonlb/vi/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2002</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">43</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1018</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume contains a number of major themes.
            Of primary importance to President Johnson was his and the Department of State’s
            continuing efforts to find a negotiated end to the war. The volume covers U.S.
            diplomatic contacts with Romania, Norway, and the Vatican to explore possible
            negotiation formulas with Hanoi in the hopes that they would lead to formal peace
            negotiations. Also covered are continued tentative prisoner of war contacts with the
            National Liberation Front in the hopes that they might lead to a separate political
            settlement. These diplomatic efforts were overshadowed by another major theme of the
            volume, the Tet Offensive and the resulting policy debate in Washington on whether to
            raise the number of U.S. troops in Vietnam. This debate led to a broader reassessment of
            U.S. policy in Vietnam, which culminated in the President’s order for a partial bombing
            halt of North Vietnam, his decision not to run for reelection, and an announcement of
            U.S. willingness to meet anywhere to negotiate peace. The search for a venue for the
            talks and attempts by advisers to convince the President to institute a full bombing
            halt comprise the final focus of the volume. Two other themes are evident in the volume,
            yet they are captured in only a few documents: the growing anti-war movement in the
            United States and the upcoming presidential elections of 1968. These two events affected
            discussions within the Johnson administration. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
