<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v19p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XIX, Part 1,
        Korea, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Korea, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XIX, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">Daniel J. Lawler</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Erin R. Mahan</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160771088</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2010</published-year>
    <published-date>2010-05-04</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1972</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">26</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">462</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents U.S. satisfaction with
            the Republic of Korea’s increasing confidence as an international actor, a result of the
            South’s burgeoning economic prosperity and its (uneven) growth in political stability.
            Park successfully thwarted efforts to improve the relationship between Japan and North
            Korea. Instead, South Korea made its own contacts with the North Korean Government, an
            initiative that yielded few tangible results but did promote regional stability.
            Nonetheless, the Nixon administration was not fully successful at allaying Seoul’s
            misgivings about two of Nixon’s most important foreign policy initiatives: the
            improvement in relations between the United States and China, and the U.S. departure
            from Vietnam. Park’s fears about U.S. reliability added to tensions that resulted from
            economic competition, especially in the textile trade.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Republic of Korea’s skepticism of the
            U.S. security guarantee was used to justify authoritarian domestic policies. In 1970
            Park and his party amended the Korean Constitution to permit his election to a third
            term as the country’s president. The following year, the two titans of late 20th century
            South Korean politics, Park Chung Hee and Kim Dae Jung, competed for the presidency.
            Department of State officials endeavored to demonstrate balance by making themselves
            available to both candidates. When Park, victorious in the 1971 election, declared
            martial law in October 1972, the U.S. Government expressed frustration with this blow to
            the Republic of Korea’s political institutions. U.S. officials feared that alliance with
            South Korea could be seen by some as implicating them in Park’s actions. Given Park’s
            determination to adopt anti-democratic measures, U.S. efforts to respond by punishing
            South Korea would likely be either ineffective or create instability there, either
            outcome potentially damaging the U.S.-Korean relationship. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
