<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v01">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume I, Foundations
        of Foreign Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Foundations of Foreign Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume I</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kristin L. Ahlberg</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160925450</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2014</published-year>
    <published-date>2014-10-29</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">40</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">835</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the intellectual
            foundations of the Jimmy Carter administration’s foreign policy. Unlike other volumes in
            the Carter subseries, the documentation seeks to illustrate the collective mindset of
            Carter administration officials on foreign policy issues in the broadest sense. Rather
            than the formulation of individual foreign policy decisions or diplomatic exchanges, the
            compilation takes as its canvas the entire record of the Carter administration. The
            volume also covers the immediate pre-presidential period, from Jimmy Carter’s December
            1974 announcement that he would campaign for the 1976 Democratic presidential nomination
            to the transition between the Gerald Ford and Carter administrations. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Specifically, the volume documents the ways
            in which the Carter administration sought to implement a foreign policy that marked a
            significant departure from the previous administrations, one characterized by an
            emphasis on issues such as human rights. The volume draws upon the published record of
            speeches, press releases, press conferences and briefings, interviews, and Congressional
            testimony to document policy positions and the assumptions of administration officials
            on the foreign policy process. The documentation presented in this volume, drawn from
            public and archival sources, chronicles the perspectives of not only President Carter
            but also Vice President Walter Mondale, President’s Assistant for National Security
            Affairs Zbigniew Brzezinski, Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, Secretary of State Edmund
            Muskie, Secretary of Defense Harold Brown, and other prominent policy makers. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
