<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v08">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume VIII, National
        Security Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">National Security Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">David W. Mabon</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/viii/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1996</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">607</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The primary focus of the documents in this
            volume is on the foreign policymaking process of the U.S. Government, including
            documentation illuminating policy formulation and major aspects and repercussions of its
            execution. Emphasis is placed on official memoranda that reveal policy positions, show
            differences within the U.S. Government over policy formulation, summarize developments
            and positions regarding an issue, contain intelligence or military assessments, and
            describe decisions or actions taken in the National Security Council. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editor sought principally to cover four
            interrelated developments in U.S. national security policy: </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1. Upon taking office, the Kennedy
            administration dismantled much of the existing policymaking machinery of the National
            Security Council (NSC) and substituted a more unstructured policymaking style. The
            President met less frequently with the full NSC than had been the case in the preceding
            Eisenhower administration. In the 1958–1960 triennium, the Council met 125 times, while
            under Presidents Kennedy and Johnson during 1961–1963, it met formally only 46 times.
            The change was progressive; while the Council convened 21 times under Kennedy in 1961,
            it met only 13 times in 1963. At the same time, the role of the President's Special
            Assistant for National Security Affairs was enhanced and the administration continuously
            created issue-oriented, ad hoc bodies to deal with specific countries and crises. From
            time to time McGeorge Bundy attempted to reintroduce more regularized policymaking
            procedures. The NSC Standing Group was one result of these efforts. Documentation
            providing some additional details on the transformed administrative role of the National
            Security Council is scheduled for volume XXV. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">2. Leading Kennedy administration
            policymakers in the White House, the Department of State, and the Department of Defense,
            but not the President himself, worked to frame a basic national security policy (BNSP),
            which would replace NSC 5906/1 of July 1959, the last such statement of policy in the
            preceding administration. While he had little interest in an umbrella BNSP paper,
            President Kennedy did from time to time set forth a multi-subject overview of U.S.
            policy, either in the full NSC meetings or with the Joint Chiefs of Staff. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">3. President Kennedy took a special interest
            in strengthening U.S. counterinsurgency capabilities. Aided by Attorney General Robert
            F. Kennedy, he constantly prodded policymakers to do more in this area. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">4. Under the leadership of Secretary of
            Defense Robert S. McNamara, the United States gradually formulated a comprehensive set
            of doctrines on strategic military posture, particularly with regard to the role of
            nuclear weapons and of conventional land-based forces. These policies evolved throughout
            the triennium and were most definitively expressed in a series of Draft Presidential
            Memoranda, or DPMs, from McNamara to the President. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
