<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v08">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume VIII,
        International Monetary and Trade Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">International Monetary and Trade Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Evan Duncan</editor>
    <editor role="primary">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Carolyn Yee</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_viii/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1998</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">30</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1018</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">On the basis of a review of already published
            documentation, such as the American Foreign Policy series, Department of State Bulletin,
            and the annual reports of the Department of the Treasury, as well as research in
            government repositories, the editors decided to focus mainly on the following subjects
            for the research and selection of documents for inclusion in this volume: 1)
            balance-of-payments matters; 2) international financial matters, including decisions by
            the International Monetary Fund and the central bank governors; 3) a series of
            international monetary crises involving sterling, gold, and the French franc; and 4)
            trade and commercial subjects. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In response to the persistent and even
            worsening U.S. balance of payments, the Johnson administration developed several
            initiatives to attempt to ameliorate the situation. Because some of the bilateral and
            multilateral financial and monetary negotiations with foreign countries became
            intertwined with balance-of-payments matters, documentation on general
            balance-of-payments policy and international financial and monetary policy was combined
            in a single compilation. The other compilation in the volume, trade and commerce, covers
            export promotion programs and bilateral tariff issues but focuses particularly on the
            complicated multilateral Kennedy Round negotiations within the context of the General
            Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
