<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v07" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume VII, Vietnam,
        July 1970–January 1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, July 1970–January 1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VII</title>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">David Goldman</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Erin R. Mahan</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160794285</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2010</published-year>
    <published-date>2010-09-08</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1970</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1972</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">37</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1089</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p>During the period covered by this volume, July 1970–January 1972, the Nixon
            administration expanded the Vietnam war into Cambodia and Laos as part of its strategy.
            This volume covers South Vietnam in the context of this larger war in Southeast Asia;
            therefore, the volume begins in July 1970 in the aftermath of the Cambodian incursion.
            At the time, a variety of topics dominated the policy discussions of President Nixon and
            his principal advisers. Among these topics were U.S. troop withdrawals, Vietnamization,
            negotiations in Paris (both the public plenary sessions and the secret talks between
            Kissinger and North Vietnamese Politburo member Le Duc Tho), and possible South
            Vietnamese operations in Cambodia, Laos, and North Vietnam. Throughout the rest of 1970
            these themes moved forward on separate paths that occasionally intersected with one
            another. South Vietnamese operations, first in Cambodia and then in Laos, were seen in
            policy terms as providing South Vietnam additional time to develop a more effective
            military, to generate economic growth, and to achieve some degree of political
            stability. The operations were also to demonstrate the success of Vietnamization and
            justify the continuing withdrawal of U.S. troops.</tei:p>
        <tei:p>In late 1970 and early 1971, the focus shifted to decision making regarding plans to
            implement a major South Vietnamese out-of-country operation called Lam Son 719, launched
            in early February 1971. The strategic purpose of the operation was to halt or slow the
            flow of military supplies to Communist forces in South Vietnam via the panhandle of
            Laos. At the same time, it would demonstrate the growing military prowess of the South
            Vietnamese Army. On the negotiating front, Kissinger continued in 1970 and
            throughout1971 to meet periodically in Paris with Le Duc Tho and other senior Vietnamese
            Communist functionaries, but made no progress. At the same time, representatives of both
            sides also met publicly in the plenary meetings. Each side used the public Paris
            meetings to exchange carefully calibrated propaganda, making the meetings, if possible,
            less productive than the secret talks. The volume focuses on the Kissinger–Le Duc Tho
            talks with only occasional documentary coverage of the public talks. </tei:p>
        <tei:p>This volume also documents President Nixon’s penchant for secret operations and
            covert warfare: his continued support for secret bombing campaigns in Cambodia and Laos
            and his approval of the November 1971 Son Tay raid into North Vietnam to rescue American
            prisoners of war. Nixon also signed off on new and continuing information gathering
            initiatives and propaganda that supported intelligence operations against Communist
            forces, organizations, and governments in South Vietnam, North Vietnam, Cambodia, and
            Laos. Additionally, he approved clandestine support for South Vietnamese political
            entities friendly to the United States. These operations are documented in some detail
            to demonstrate the role of covert actions in support of overt political and military
            operations. </tei:p>
        <tei:p>In the waning months of the period covered by this volume, deadlock had set in.
            Neither side appeared able to win militarily, or even to weaken his adversary
            sufficiently to make him negotiate in good faith. There were signs, however, that Hanoi
            might be preparing to mount a major military effort in 1972. Its purpose would be to
            break through this impasse without having to travel a diplomatic path. The volume
            concludes at this point.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
