<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v08">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume VIII,
        Arab-Israeli Dispute, January 1977–August 1978</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Arab-Israeli Dispute, January 1977–August 1978</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160921018</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2013</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2013</published-year>
    <published-date>2013-10-04</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1978</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">26</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1338</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the most important
            foreign policy issues of the Jimmy Carter administration. The focus of this volume is
            the Carter administration’s efforts to help negotiate settlements to the Arab-Israeli
            dispute. The volume begins in January 1977, and documents the administration’s immediate
            efforts to find a comprehensive settlement between Israel and Egypt, Syria, Jordan, and
            Lebanon, and to seek a resolution for Palestinians living in the West Bank and Gaza. The
            first part of the volume documents the administration’s initiatives to reconvene the
            Geneva Conference, which was first established in December 1973 to find a comprehensive
            settlement to the Arab-Israeli dispute. After talks with the various parties stagnated
            and Sadat made his momentous visit to Jerusalem in November 1977, the administration
            came to view a bilateral negotiation between Egypt and Israel as the most realistic
            avenue to an eventual settlement. Accordingly, the portion of the volume covering the
            period from December 1977 to August 1978 documents the ways in which the administration
            worked to find a path to a bilateral peace agreement that would also include limited
            self-rule for Palestinians living in the West Bank and Gaza. The volume concludes with
            the White House announcement of a summit to be held at Camp David, Maryland in September
            1978, where U.S. officials would work in seclusion with Egyptian and Israeli officials
            in an attempt to produce an agreement.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
