<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1981-88v11">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1981–1988, Volume XI, START
        I</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1981-88" type="sub-series">1981–1988</title>
    <title type="volume">START I</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XI</title>
    <editor role="primary">James Graham Wilson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2021</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2021</published-year>
    <published-date>2021-04-22</published-date>
    <administration>reagan</administration>
    <grouping administration="reagan">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1981</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1988</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">28</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1582</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This is the first of two volumes in the
                <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series devoted to the START I
            agreement (the “Treaty Between the United States of America and the Union of the Soviet
            Socialist Republics on the Reduction and Limitation of Strategic Offensive Arms”), which
            President George H.W. Bush and Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev signed on July 29, 1991.
            It begins in the summer of 1981, when the Reagan administration recast the Strategic
            Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) as the Strategic Arms Reduction Talks (START) and concludes
            in early 1989 with the presidential transition to the Bush administration. Covered here
            are the initial rounds of negotiations in Geneva from June 1982 to November 1983; the
            incorporation of START into the Nuclear and Space Arms Talks (NST) in March 1985; the
            five meetings between Reagan and Gorbachev between 1985 and 1988; and the internal U.S.
            deliberations on strategic arms negotiations throughout these periods. Given the pivotal
            role of strategic defenses in negotiations on strategic arms reductions, deliberations
            and instructions pertaining to the Defense and Space Talks are also included in this
            volume.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
