<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v13">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XIII, Western
        Europe Region</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Western Europe Region</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Charles S. Sampson</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xiii/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1995</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">30</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">816</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation printed in this volume
            highlights U.S. policy toward European economic and political integration, U.S.
            participation in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), and the U.S. attitude
            toward the Multilateral Force (MLF) and Atlantic Nuclear Force (ANF). It further
            discusses the position of the United States with regard to the question of nuclear
            sharing within the Atlantic community. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Because of the extensive amount of
            documentation on U.S. participation in NATO, the editors selected summaries of the North
            Atlantic Council Ministerial meetings and summary records of the visits of the NATO
            Secretaries General to Washington, during which long series of conversations were held.
            The editors also focused on documenting the U.S. response to French withdrawal from the
            NATO military command structure in March 1966. President Johnson set the tone of the
            response and Francis Bator of the National Security Council Staff coordinated the
            details of the policy. For the period after the 1968 Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia,
            the editors selected documentation that shows that the White House took an active role
            in the formulation of policy toward NATO. The editors also selected reports from posts
            in Brussels, London, and Paris to document U.S. policy toward the general question of
            European economic and political integration and toward the second British application
            for membership in the Common Market in 1967. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
