<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v20">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XX, Eastern
        Europe</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Eastern Europe</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Carl Ashley</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Mircea A. Munteanu</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160931154</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2015</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2015</published-year>
    <published-date>2015-11-30</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1981</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">44</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1023</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the most important
            foreign policy issues of the Jimmy Carter administration. The focus of this volume is on
            U.S. policy toward the Communist countries of Eastern Europe, except Poland.
            Documentation on Poland will be published in a separate volume.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume illustrates the Carter
            administration’s efforts to transform the long-standing U.S. policy of differentiation
            between Eastern European nations by including human rights performance in its policy
            assessment. This allowed for a warming of relations with countries that exhibited
            internally liberal policies, even if its foreign policy continued to be viewed as
            subservient to Soviet interests. The administration continued to support Romania as a
            Communist-bloc critic of the Soviet Union, despite strained relations over a series of
            high-profile defections, and planned for support of Yugoslavia’s integrity and
            sovereignty after the death of Josip Broz Tito. U.S. relations with Bulgaria,
            Czechoslovakia, and the German Democratic Republic remained distant throughout the
            administration, but the modified policy of differentiation led to the return of the
            Crown of St. Stephen to Hungary. The administration also expanded broadcasting toward
            Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, especially following the Soviet invasion of
            Afghanistan.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
