<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v39">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXXIX, European
        Security</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">European Security</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXXIX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Douglas E. Selvage</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/xxxix/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2008</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">38</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1131</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume focuses on the topic of European
            Security, a key foreign policy concern for both the Nixon and Ford administrations. It
            is centered around the basic questions the U.S. Government faced: how best to achieve
            security and cooperation in Europe, and how to reduce both NATO and Warsaw Pact forces
            in Europe. This volume has a broader scope than most, and covers the entire span of both
            the Nixon and Ford administrations, 1969–1976. While the general focus is European
            security, the specific focus is on two overriding issues that faced the Nixon and Ford
            administrations: 1) whether to hold a conference on European security attended by the
            United States and its NATO allies, and the Soviet Union and its Warsaw Pact allies; and
            2) whether the United States and its European allies would negotiate an agreement with
            the Soviet Union and its East European allies on mutual and balanced force reductions
            (MBFR) in Europe. Both President Richard M. Nixon and Henry A. Kissinger (Assistant to
            the President for National Security Affairs, and after September 1973, Secretary of
            State) were skeptical that a conference on European security would achieve very
            much—they believed that the Europeans were overestimating its potential impact. There
            were also related issues, such as whether to combine the security conference with
            negotiations on force reductions. In addition, the question of negotiations with the
            NATO allies looms large in the volume, which includes many memoranda of conversation
            between U.S. officials and their NATO counterparts.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
