<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v29p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXIX, Part 1,
        Korea</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Korea</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIX, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">Karen L. Gatz</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xxix/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2000</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">829</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The first section of the volume deals with
            U.S.-Republic of Korea relations during a period of strife and violence on the Korean
            peninsula unknown since the Korean War. The year 1964 was marked by an internal crisis
            within the Republic of Korea as students and opponents of the government of President
            Pak Chong-hui (Park Chung Нее) took to the streets in violent opposition to the
            government's alleged corruption and the potential treaty between the Republic of Korea
            and Japan. The government responded with the imposition of martial law. After the end of
            1964, internal opposition lessened, but the threat from North Korea grew. In 1967,
            border clashes along the 38th parallel and infiltration of North Korean saboteurs
            increased. The culmination of this campaign occurred in January 1968 when North Korean
            commandos attacked the Blue House (the presidential residence in Seoul) in a brazen
            attempt to assassinate President Pak. A few days later North Korea seized the U.S.S.
            Pueblo and its crew. The United States was faced with South Korean demands for
            retaliatory action, and a serious crisis of confidence in Seoul. The volume documents
            how the Johnson administration responded, both in this first compilation and in the one
            on the Pueblo, to the strong possibility of renewed war on the Korean peninsula. The
            basic theme of the compilation is the Johnson administration's de-escalation of the
            crisis. The final major theme of this first compilation is the close personal
            relationship between Presidents Pak and Johnson and how this resulted in South Korea's
            support for the war in Vietnam. The second compilation, on the Pueblo crisis, begins
            with records of the almost daily meetings of President Johnson with his key military,
            intelligence, and diplomatic advisers to examine contingency options, none particularly
            good and some that were dangerous. After it became clear that a military response was
            unacceptable, the United States relied on a campaign of diplomacy, including using
            whatever influence the Soviet Union would bring to bear on North Korea, shows of U.S.
            force, and direct negotiations with North Korea at Panmunjom. The final and smallest
            section of the volume documents U.S. efforts to convince both Japan and Korea to settle
            their outstanding differences and sign in June 1965 and ratify that December a Treaty on
            Basic Relations. The compilation documents the high-level pressure brought by the
            Johnson administration on the two allies to resolve their longstanding
            differences.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
