<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v11">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XI, Arms
        Control and Disarmament</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Arms Control and Disarmament</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Evans Gerakas</editor>
    <editor role="primary">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Carolyn B. Yee</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xi/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1997</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">36</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">801</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editors have reviewed the already
            published official record, particularly the annual publication of the U.S. Arms Control
            and Disarmament Agency, Documents on Disarmament, and have examined documentation
            available in government repositories. They decided to focus the record published in this
            volume on the following subjects: 1) levels of production of fissionable materials for
            nuclear weapons production; 2) negotiation of the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty; 3)
            negotiation of the Outer Space Treaty; 4) seabed arms control policies and discussions;
            5) nuclear testing policy and its relationship to a possible comprehensive test ban
            agreement; and 6) the origins of the talks with the Soviet Union on strategic offensive
            missile and defensive anti-missile systems. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume presents a comprehensive
            collection of the records of the Committee of Principals, a high-level interagency group
            that formulated policies on arms control issues for the President's approval. It also
            presents the authoritative record of the correspondence between President Johnson and
            Nikita Khrushchev and Alexei Kosygin, the President's Soviet counterparts, on
            disarmament matters. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume includes intelligence information,
            such as the ability to verify possible arms control agreements, which is contained in
            National Intelligence Estimates and memoranda prepared in the Department of State's
            Bureau of Intelligence and Research. The editors did not, however, attempt to document
            the more technical and scientific dimensions of verification or to explore fully the
            scope and impact of intelligence gathering on arms control policies. Nor did they seek
            to document the intelligence available to top policymakers regarding the activities and
            intentions of the Soviet Union in the arms control area. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
