<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v06">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume VI, Vietnam,
        January 1969–July 1970</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Vietnam, January 1969–July 1970</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume VI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Carolyn Yee</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/vi/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2006</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">38</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1173</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The scope of this volume is different from
            previous volumes on Vietnam in the Foreign Relations series. For the years 1955–1968 the
            series produced volumes exclusively on U.S. policy towards Vietnam and documented U.S.
            policy towards Laos and Cambodia in separate volumes. With the Nixon administration’s
            decision to take the war to the enemy in Cambodia and integrate more fully the secret
            war in Laos into its strategy for Vietnam, this format was no longer valid. This volume
            covers Vietnam in the context of the larger war that included the conflicts in Laos and
            Cambodia, and in the case of the former, also the role of Thailand in Laos.
            Consequently, the editors had to make choices about what to cover. When Vietnam was the
            main concern of President Nixon and his principal advisers—primarily Assistant for
            National Security Affairs Henry Kissinger and his NSC Staff; Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker
            in Saigon; Commander of the Military Assistance Command, Vietnam, General Creighton
            Abrams; and Chief Paris Peace Talks negotiator, Henry Cabot Lodge—the focus is on
            Vietnam strategy, planning and operations. The focus of the volume later shifts to the
            issue of the deterioration of the secret war in Laos in March 1970. In March and April
            1970, after the overthrow of Prince Norodom Sihanouk of Cambodia and his replacement by
            pro-American General Lon Nol, the volume moves its focus to Cambodia, culminating with
            the U.S.-South Vietnamese invasion of that country in an effort to attack the North
            Vietnamese troops in their sanctuaries. The volume concludes with the withdrawal of U.S.
            forces from Cambodia. In addition to this shifting emphasis on Vietnam, Laos, and
            Cambodia, the volume has as one of its principal themes the search for a negotiated
            settlement to the Vietnam War.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
