<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v21">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XXI, Cyprus;
        Turkey; Greece</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Cyprus; Turkey; Greece</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXI</title>
    <editor role="primary">David Zierler</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-092305-0</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2014</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2014</published-year>
    <published-date>2014-04-03</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">32</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">660</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the most important
            foreign policy issues of the Jimmy Carter administration. The focus of this volume is on
            U.S. policy towards the Eastern Mediterranean region. The Carter administration’s major
            goals during this period were to broker a peace deal to unify Cyprus, which was divided
            since the Turkish invasion of 1974; to lift the arms embargo enacted by Congress on
            Turkey as a result of the invasion; and to reintegrate Greece into the NATO military
            alliance, from which Athens had withdrawn in protest of Turkey’s actions in Cyprus.
            President Carter was keenly interested in securing a negotiated settlement between the
            divided Greek and Turkish Cypriot communities, and he made it a high-level priority at
            the outset of his term. Despite intensive efforts headed by the Department of State and
            Carter’s emissary Clark Clifford, an agreement to unify Cyprus eluded the Carter
            administration; today the island remains divided. The Carter administration was more
            successful in its campaign on Capitol Hill to lift the arms embargo on Turkey, thereby
            alleviating a significant source of tension between Washington and Ankara, while at the
            same time convincing the Greek leadership to re-join NATO’s military command structure.
            Although the Carter administration was unable to resolve the Cyprus dispute, it secured
            a significant diplomatic and strategic victory by ensuring that NATO’s southern tier was
            much stronger by the time President Carter left office. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
