<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v24">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXIV,
        Africa</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Africa</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIV</title>
    <editor role="primary">Nina Davis Howland</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xxiv/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1995</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">47</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1144</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume focuses on the issues that
            primarily engaged high-level U.S. policymakers. Major topics include: U.S. efforts to
            strengthen North African ties to the West and forestall Soviet attempts to dominate any
            part of the region; the attempts of U.S. policymakers to find a basis for improved
            relations with Algeria without prejudicing the good relations enjoyed with Morocco and
            Tunisia; the desire of the United States to preserve Moroccan independence and unity;
            continuation of substantial U.S. economic and military aid to Morocco and Tunisia; U.S.
            efforts to preserve the independence and stability of Libya; renegotiation of the 1954
            Wheelus Base agreement with the hope of prolonging U.S. retention of the base despite
            Libya's announced intention of not renewing the agreement; U.S. efforts to strengthen
            ties with the countries of Sub-Saharan Africa and prevent them from falling under
            Communist domination; a revitalized and strengthened policy toward Africa following a
            review of African development policies and programs (the Korry Report) ordered by
            President Johnson in May 1966; U.S. efforts to maintain friendly relations with
            Nkrumah's successor following the February 1966 overthrow of his authoritarian and
            anti-Western regime in Ghana; U.S. support for peaceful resolution of Somali-Ethiopian
            border conflicts in the strategically important Horn of Africa; the U.S. effort to
            maintain a close relationship with Ethiopia, with its important U.S. military base at
            Kagnew Station and the largest Military Assistance Program in Africa, while maintaining
            good relations with Somalia; the U.S. policy of non-intervention and advocacy of
            negotiation and compromise following the July 1967 outbreak of civil war in Nigeria; the
            tension between U.S. support for reform and self-determination in Portugal's African
            colonies of Angola and Mozambique, on the one hand, and the U.S. and Portuguese
            membership in NATO, which granted the United States important military base rights in
            the Azores, on the other; U.S. support for British efforts to guarantee universal adult
            suffrage before granting Rhodesia full independence, and for mandatory UN economic
            sanctions against Rhodesia following the white minority government's Unilateral
            Declaration of Independence in November 1965; U.S. condemnation of apartheid while
            opposing mandatory UN economic sanctions against South Africa; and U.S. support for UN
            termination of South Africa's mandate to administer South West Africa. The editors
            included a selection of intelligence estimates and analyses seen by high-level
            policymakers, especially those that were sent to President Johnson. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
