<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v03">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume III, Foreign
        Economic Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Foreign Economic Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume III</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160920851</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2013</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2013</published-year>
    <published-date>2013-09-17</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">34</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1155</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the most important
            issues in the foreign policy of the administration of Jimmy Carter. During Carter’s term
            as president, accelerating inflation, oil shortages, persistent trade deficits, and the
            declining value of the U.S. dollar challenged U.S. strength at home and abroad. This
            volume documents the Carter administration’s response to these challenges in its
            international monetary and trade policies, as well as its involvement in the annual
            Group of Seven (G–7) economic summit meetings, covering topics such as the completion of
            the Tokyo Round of trade negotiations held under the aegis of the General Agreement on
            Tariffs and Trade; the provision of assistance to domestic producers facing import
            competition in sectors such as steel, shoes, and textiles; efforts to convince Japan to
            open its markets wider to U.S. exports; attempts to arrest the sharp decline of the U.S.
            dollar; and industrialized country economic policy coordination in the G–7. The volume
            also examines the administration’s approach to North-South economic relations and
            commodity policy, covering issues such as foreign aid; U.S. involvement in
            development-focused international financial institutions; the creation of the Common
            Fund; world hunger; debt relief for less developed counties; and technology
            transfer.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
