<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1950-55Intel">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1950–1955, The Intelligence
        Community, 1950–1955</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1945-02-intel-retrospective" type="sub-series"/>
    <title type="volume">The Intelligence Community, 1950–1955</title>
    <title type="volume-number"/>
    <editor role="primary">Douglas Keane</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Michael Warner</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/truman/c24687.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2007</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>truman</administration>
    <administration>eisenhower</administration>
    <grouping administration="truman eisenhower">retrospective</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1950</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1955</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">30</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">839</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is organized along chronological
            lines in one large chapter covering 1950–1955, and a second chapter that includes the
            key National Security Council Intelligence Directives of the period. The volume
            documents the institutional growth of the intelligence community during the first half
            of the 1950s. When Lt. General Walter Bedell Smith took over as Director of Central
            Intelligence in October 1950, he inherited an agency that was widely believed to have
            been unable to establish itself as the central institution of the U.S. intelligence
            community. Utilizing his great prestige, and a national security directive from
            President Truman, Smith established the multiple directorate structure within the
            Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) that has continued to this day, brought the
            clandestine service into the CIA, and worked to effect greater inter-agency coordination
            through a strengthened process to produce National Intelligence Estimates. The
            exponential growth of the national security establishment and of the intelligence
            community was due to the impact of two factors: NSC 68 (a clarion call for more active
            containment of the Soviet Union) and the Korean War. The Central Intelligence Agency was
            called upon to expand the clandestine service, and the intelligence community was
            required to provide better and more definitive intelligence on the Soviet bloc and
            China. When Allen Dulles took over as Director of Central Intelligence in February 1953,
            these pressures continued. By 1955, the general consensus of two commissions appointed
            by President Eisenhower to review the intelligence effort was that the clandestine
            service had grown too rapidly and was plagued by poor management. In general, the
            commission implied that the clandestine service’s growth had come at the expense of the
            agency’s intelligence analysts.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
