<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v23">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XXIII:
        Southeast Asia</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Southeast Asia</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="worldcat">http://worldcat.org/oclc/32184269</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1994</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">33</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1037</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In selecting documents for inclusion in
            volume XXIII, the editor focused on the actions of President Kennedy and his immediate
            advisers at the White House and elsewhere in the government in formulating policy with
            respect to Southeast Asia. This volume documents the meetings of the President with his
            advisers from the White House, the Department of State, and other agencies, as well as
            the written advice to the President from these advisers. The editors have also included
            the major internal U.S. Government policy recommendations and decision papers relating
            to Southeast Asia. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the compilation on Indonesia, the role the
            United States played in expediting the transfer of West New Guinea from the Netherlands
            to Indonesia meant that much of the documentation printed relates to consultations with
            the two parties to the dispute. In the case of the confrontation between Indonesia and
            the British Commonwealth over the formation of Malaysia, consultations with the British
            and Australians become equally important. In the compilation on the Philippines, the
            role of the U.S. Congress is highlighted. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Intelligence assessments regarding Southeast
            Asia are reflected in documents selected for publication here. The capabilities of
            Indonesia and the Netherlands in a potential conflict over West New Guinea was a key
            intelligence question. Thailand's ability to meet the threat of Communist insurgency in
            its northeast region was another. Cambodia's orientation vis-a-vis the West and East was
            still another. The editor did not, however, attempt to document the details of
            operational activities by intelligence authorities in connection with Southeast Asia.
        </tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>joewiz</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>joewiz</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>chalouma</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-08-30T11:00:50.667-05:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
