<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v17p2">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XVII, Part 2,
        Sub-Saharan Africa</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Sub-Saharan Africa</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVII, Part 2</title>
    <editor role="primary">Louise P. Woodroofe</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-094796-4</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2018</published-year>
    <published-date>2018-10-25</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">463</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the foreign policy
            decisions of the administration of President Jimmy Carter. Parts 1 and 3 of Volume XVII
            address the Horn of Africa and North Africa, respectively. The focus of this volume is
            on the Carter administration’s approach to events in Africa. The first chapter addresses
            the administration’s attitude toward the continent as a whole, including an attempt to
            reconstruct U.S. foreign policy toward Africa while continuing its predecessors’ policy
            of countering Cuban and Soviet influence on the continent. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume is also divided into regional
            subsections: First, the chapter on East Africa covers the U.S. response to the
            provocations of Idi Amin in Uganda, the Tanzanian invasion to overthrow the Ugandan
            dictator, and a strengthening of ties with Tanzania and Kenya to further U.S. interests
            in southern Africa. Next, the chapter on Central Africa outlines U.S.-Zairean relations,
            focusing on the Shaba II crisis as well as aid to and investment in Sudan and parts of
            the Sahel. Finally, the chapter on West Africa addresses the role of Nigeria in African
            economics and politics, the U.S. response to a Liberian coup, and U.S. relations with
            the other smaller countries in West Africa.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
