<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v03">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume III, Foreign
        Economic Policy; International Monetary Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Foreign Economic Policy; International Monetary Policy, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume III</title>
    <editor role="primary">Bruce F. Duncombe</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/iii/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2001</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">28</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">674</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Compared with their ongoing preoccupation
            with international political and strategic policy, President Nixon and his Assistant for
            National Security Affairs, Henry Kissinger, did not express much interest in foreign
            economic matters. They nonetheless understood that domestic and foreign economic
            developments could have profound effects on their political programs and goals. In
            particular, the Nixon administration inherited a serious U.S. balance-of-payments
            deficit, which threatened to destabilize the international economic system. During the
            first term, 1969–1972, Nixon administration officials undertook an intensive
            re-evaluation of U.S. monetary and trade policies. From this reappraisal came several
            foreign economic initiatives, many of which were formulated in the Department of the
            Treasury, to try to stop the flow of U.S. capital abroad. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The first part of this volume documents the
            various foreign economic options that Nixon administration officials considered in
            trying to alleviate the balance-of-payments problem. Some of the following proposals
            were stillborn, but others became Nixon administration initiatives: reduction in
            non-military U.S. personnel stationed overseas; efforts to get Japan and especially West
            Germany to offset the costs of the U.S. military presence abroad with the purchase of
            more U.S. military equipment; reduction in the Interest Equalization Tax; revaluation of
            exchange rates of countries with trade surpluses; opposition to foreign governments'
            preferential trade policies; reductions in foreign aid; and reform of the international
            monetary system. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The second part of this volume treats the
            administration's interest in reform of the international monetary system. President
            Nixon and his economic advisers increasingly believed that the creation of a new
            economic system could alleviate major U.S. fiscal problems, such as tariff inequities
            and declining gold reserves. One proposal called for major European nations' acceptance
            of the International Monetary Fund's plan of Special Drawing Rights (SDRs). Another
            called for flexible exchange rates. Nixon administration officials hoped to persuade
            individual countries, especially in Europe, to devalue or revalue their currencies,
            abolish fund controls, and agree on common trading rules, all of which would avert a
            large-scale financial crisis and promote international trade. Ultimately, the collapse
            of the British pound and European disagreements over currency revaluation prompted
            President Nixon to announce his New Economic Policy in August 1971, which ended the
            convertibility of dollars to gold and imposed a 10 percent surcharge on imports, as well
            as imposing domestic wage and price controls for 90 days. </tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>joewiz</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>joewiz</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2010-04-26T10:35:00.418-05:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>chalouma</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-08-30T11:00:50.667-05:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
