<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76ve15p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume E–15, Part 1,
        Documents on Eastern Europe, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Documents on Eastern Europe, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume E–15, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">Peter Kraemer</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/e15/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="epub"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2008</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">551</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation in this volume highlights
            U.S. policy toward Eastern Europe from 1973–1976 in the period of détente. Relations
            with the communist-dominated states of Eastern Europe warmed during this period,
            building on the progress made during Nixon's first term, the afterglow of détente with
            the Soviet Union, and U.S. withdrawal from Vietnam. The documents opening this volume
            affirm that U.S. foreign policy still perceived Eastern Europe's collective status as
            “captive nations” under Soviet domination but held hopes for improved bilateral
            relations on a country-by-country basis. The Nixon and Ford administrations' ambitions
            for improved relations with Hungary and Czechoslovakia remained unrealized, and U.S.
            contacts with Bulgaria and Albania were extremely limited. Documentation on these
            countries is contained only in the Eastern Europe Regional chapter. The majority of this
            volume focuses on those countries with which the United States had major continuing
            bilateral relations, evident in new or improved economic, cultural, and
            political-military relations: Romania, Yugoslavia, and Poland. These three countries,
            the Administration hoped, were most likely to assert their independence from Moscow.
            Finally, although the United States officially established diplomatic ties to the German
            Democratic Republic during this period, relations remained limited and evidenced a
            continuing low level of tension over the status of divided Berlin.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
