<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1958-60v12">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1958–1960, Near East Region;
        Iraq; Iran; Arabian Peninsula, Volume XII</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1958-60" type="sub-series">1958–1960</title>
    <title type="volume">Near East Region; Iraq; Iran; Arabian Peninsula</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="madison"
        >http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS195860v12</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1992</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>eisenhower</administration>
    <grouping administration="eisenhower">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1958</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1960</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">29</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">846</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume focuses on the diplomatic and
            political, economic and, to a lesser extent, military aspects of U.S. foreign policy
            related to the Near East Region, Iraq, Iran, and the countries of the Arabian Peninsula
            during the Eisenhower administration, with an emphasis on policy deliberation and
            formulation. Documents illustrate the leading role of the Department of State,
            reflecting the influence of Secretary of State John Foster Dulles within the Eisenhower
            administration’s foreign policy process and the fact that the Department was the most
            important point of contact for the Arab world.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The central emphasis of this volume is the
            political and diplomatic effort by the Eisenhower administration to confront and
            eventually to come to terms with radical Arab nationalism as personified by President
            Abdul Gamal Nasser of the United Arab Republic and Prime Minister Abdul Karim Qassim of
            Iraq. At the same time, the volume illustrates U.S. concern with encouraging the more
            pro-Western Middle East monarchies, Saudi Arabia and Iran, to enact policies that would
            protect them from such radicalism. Another important goal of this volume was to present
            representative documentation on high-level U.S.-British diplomatic consultation on the
            Middle East, a region of traditional British influence. This theme appears most vividly
            in the documentation on British protected states, such as Kuwait, but it underlies most
            of the volume. In addition, much of the documentation presented in this volume reflects
            the Eisenhower administration’s concern about the influence of the Soviet Union in the
            region.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. oil policy also plays a crucial role in
            U.S. relations with many of the countries in this volume. It is one of the themes of the
            regional compilation and underlies the relationship with Saudi Arabia and, to a lesser,
            extent Iran. Additionally, military questions, especially the United States role in the
            Baghdad Pact (later, Central Treaty Organization) and military assistance to Iran, form
            an important theme of this volume.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
