<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v28">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXVIII,
        Laos</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Laos</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXVIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xxviii/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1998</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">32</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">809</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editor of volume XXVIII developed eight
            areas of specific focus for the selection. (1) Formulation of policy in Washington on
            providing U.S. support for the air and ground war in Laos either by U.S. support of Lao
            Armed Forces or by U.S. direct actions. (2) U.S. policy decisions in Washington in
            conjunction with U.S. officials in Laos to support the neutralist Souvanna Phouma
            government against both its right-wing and Pathet Lao opponents. (3) Unsuccessful
            efforts to reach a new negotiated settlement on Laos to replace the failed Geneva
            settlement of 1962, especially through the influence and good services of the Soviet
            Union. (4) The campaign to interdict logistical supplies traveling down the Laos portion
            of the Ho Chi Minh Trail destined to support Viet Cong and North Vietnamese forces in
            South Vietnam and the bureaucratic battle for control of the ground intelligence on and
            harassment of these interdiction operations that was fought between the Ambassador in
            Laos and the Military Assistance Commander, Vietnam. (5) The Central Intelligence Agency
            's support and direction of Meo (H'mong) and other tribal anti-North Vietnamese
            guerrillas. (6) The intelligence assessment controversy over the amount of North
            Vietnamese infiltration down the Ho Chi Minh Trail and the effectiveness of U.S.
            interdiction efforts. (7) The campaign by Secretary of Defense Robert McNamara to apply
            technology to the campaign against infiltration and to apply appropriate technology in
            the controversy over whether jet aircraft or propeller driven aircraft were more suited
            to the warfare in Laos. (8) The establishment and then the loss to North Vietnamese
            forces of U.S.-manned site 85 at Phou Pha Thi, the major navigation aide in northern
            Laos for the bombing campaign against North Vietnam. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
