<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v19">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XIX, South
        Asia</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">South Asia</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XIX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Louis J. Smith</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/c14994.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1996</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">25</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">759</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume focuses upon the Kennedy
            administration's efforts to reorient U.S. policy with respect to South Asia by improving
            relations with India while maintaining the established alliance relationship with
            Pakistan. It includes documentation on the impact of the Kashmir dispute between India
            and Pakistan, the Indian invasion of Portuguese Goa, and the impact of the Pushtunistan
            dispute between Pakistan and Afghanistan. It documents U.S. efforts to counter Soviet
            influence in Afghanistan and India, as well as the attempt to take advantage of the
            border war between India and China that developed in 1962 in order to forge a closer
            relationship between the United States and India. In general, the emphasis is on
            political developments, but documents are included on significant economic concerns,
            including the use of developmental economic assistance as an important element in the
            revised policy approach to South Asia. The primary issues, interests, and factors in
            U.S. policy toward South Asia during this period were often interwoven and affected each
            other subtly or in clear linkages. The editor determined that a chronological
            compilation offered a more accurate, comprehensible, and economical presentation of the
            relevant documentation than a division of the official record according to bilateral
            relations with particular governments. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
