<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v16">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XVI, Eastern
        Europe; Cyprus; Greece; Turkey</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Eastern Europe; Cyprus; Greece; Turkey</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XVI</title>
    <editor role="primary">James E. Miller</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xvi/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1994</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">22</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">788</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation printed in this volume
            presents the major actions and discussions of the U.S. Government toward the states of
            Eastern Europe (Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Poland, Romania, and Yugoslavia),
            three states of the Eastern Mediterranean (Greece, Cyprus, and Turkey), and Austria and
            Finland. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A single Eastern European regional
            compilation includes documentation on U.S. relations with Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia,
            Hungary, and Romania. In general, these documents illustrate the very limited contacts
            between the United States and these satellite nations and focus primarily on limited
            economic ties. Documentation on Hungarian efforts to secure a seat in the United Nations
            will be printed in volume XXV, General; United Nations. The documentation on Poland
            focuses on U.S. efforts to employ limited economic assistance as a tool to gain
            diplomatic leverage with an important Warsaw Pact state. Documentation relating to
            Yugoslavia deals with the continuing U.S. policy of providing support to this Communist
            state in order to ensure its independence from Soviet control. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Eastern Mediterranean was an area of
            growing tension and instability during the early 1960s. The Cyprus portion of the volume
            outlines U.S. efforts to promote intercommunal harmony and to establish a firm working
            relationship with the government of the newly independent Cypriot Republic.
            Documentation on Greece and Turkey deals with U.S. efforts to provide military and
            economic assistance to these two states and ensure their domestic political stability. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume also provides coverage of U.S.
            relations with two important neutral nations bordering on the Soviet Bloc. Documentation
            on Austria deals primarily with U.S.-Austrian discussions regarding improvements in
            Austrian defense capabilities. Documentation on Finland outlines the U.S. response to
            the Finno-Soviet crisis of November 1961 and subsequent U.S. efforts to bolster Finnish
            security and independence, including the question of arms supply. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
