<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v38p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXXVIII, Part
        1, Foundations of Foreign Policy, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Foundations of Foreign Policy, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXXVIII, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Kristin L. Ahlberg </editor>
    <editor role="primary">Alexander R. Wieland</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160895302</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2012</published-year>
    <published-date>2012-08-29</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">30</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">508</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the intellectual
            foundations of the foreign policy of the second Richard Nixon administration and the
            Gerald Ford administration. Unlike other volumes in the Nixon/Ford subseries, the
            documentation seeks to illustrate the collective mindset of Nixon and Ford
            administration officials on foreign policy issues in the broadest sense. Rather than the
            formulation of individual foreign policy decisions or diplomatic exchanges, the
            compilation takes as its canvas the entire record of the second Nixon administration and
            the Ford administration’s efforts to develop a grand strategy in foreign policymaking.
            Specifically, the volume charts the ways in which internal and external pressures,
            during a period of profound political drama at home and abroad, affected this process.
            It elucidates the primary intellectual themes that ran through and influenced both Nixon
            and Ford’s foreign policy: a continued belief in interdependence and cooperation in
            relation to energy and economic issues, an emphasis upon East-West détente, and the
            primacy of the executive branch in the formulation and conduct of foreign policy. In
            addition, the volume looks at the ways in which the Nixon and Ford administrations
            developed strategies to contend with a changing geopolitical landscape in the aftermath
            of U.S. withdrawal from Southeast Asia, a new intensification of the Cold War in Africa,
            conflict in the Middle East, and the proliferation of transnational issues. Lastly, the
            volume explores the influence of domestic politics on the making of foreign policy, most
            notably during the late stages of the Watergate scandal, the resignation of President
            Nixon, and the ideological challenges posed by Ronald Reagan and Jimmy Carter during the
            1976 Presidential campaign. The documentation presented in the volume, drawn from public
            and archival sources, chronicles the perspectives of not only Nixon and Ford but also
            Secretaries of State William Rogers and Henry Kissinger, Secretaries of Defense Melvin
            Laird and James Schlesinger, and other prominent policy makers.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
