<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1981-88v01">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1981–1988, Volume I, Foundations
        of Foreign Policy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1981-88" type="sub-series">1981–1988</title>
    <title type="volume">Foundations of Foreign Policy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume I</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kristin L. Ahlberg</editor>
    <editor role="general">Kathleen B. Rasmussen</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978-0-16-095933-2</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2022</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2022</published-year>
    <published-date>2022-09-09</published-date>
    <administration>reagan</administration>
    <grouping administration="reagan">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1981</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1988</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">68</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1565</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a subseries of volumes
            of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> series that documents the
            foreign policy decisions of the administration of President Ronald Reagan. This volume
            documents the intellectual foundations of the foreign policy pursued by President Ronald
            Reagan’s administration. Unlike other volumes in the Reagan subseries, the documentation
            seeks to illuminate the collective mindset of Reagan administration officials across
            foreign policy issues in the broadest sense.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Rather than exploring the formulation of
            individual policy decisions or diplomatic exchanges, the volume takes as its canvas the
            entire 8-year record of the administration, as well as the immediate pre-presidential
            period, including the transition between the Jimmy Carter and Reagan administrations.
            Specifically, it documents the ways in which the Reagan administration tried to “reset”
            foreign policy following the Vietnam War, Watergate scandal, and Iranian hostage crisis
            and it sought to recreate a world structure hospitable to certain U.S. values. The
            volume draws upon both the published record of speeches, press releases, press
            conferences and briefings, interviews, and Congressional testimony and the internal
            memoranda, correspondence, meeting minutes, and other records generated by
            administration officials to document the policy positions and assumptions of foreign
            policy makers. The documentation presented in this volume, drawn from public and
            archival sources, chronicles the perspectives of not only President Reagan but also Vice
            President George H.W. Bush, Secretaries of State Alexander Haig and George Shultz,
            Secretary of Defense Caspar Weinberger, and other prominent policy makers.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
