<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v21">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXI, Near East
        Region; Arabian Peninsula</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Near East Region; Arabian Peninsula</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXI</title>
    <editor role="primary">Nina Davis Howland</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/vol_xxi/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2000</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">919</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume focuses on the issues that
            primarily engaged high-level policymakers. Major topics include: 1) U.S. efforts to
            prevent the Soviet Union from gaining influence in the strategically located and
            oil-rich Near East region; 2) the attempts of U.S. policymakers to pro-mote peace and
            stability in the region and to avoid being drawn into either inter-Arab or Arab-Israeli
            disputes; 3) U.S. efforts to preserve access to the region's oil supplies by maintaining
            and strengthening its position in the moderate Arab states, especially Kuwait and Saudi
            Arabia; 4) reiteration of the long-standing U.S. commitment to Saudi Arabia's
            territorial integrity in the event of unprovoked aggression, while warning that such
            support would be difficult if Saudi involvement in Yemen provoked military confrontation
            with the United Arab Republic; 5) U.S. military assistance to the Saudi armed forces
            combined with support for a Saudi program of political, social, and economic progress;
            6) the attempts of U.S. policymakers to prevent the escalation and spread of the civil
            war in Yemen by encouraging a negotiated settlement; 7) the attempts of U.S.
            policymakers to delay British withdrawal from South Arabia and the Persian Gulf; 8) U.S.
            support for British efforts to negotiate an orderly and peaceful transition to
            independence for Aden and the British Protectorates in South Arabia; 9) U.S. efforts to
            maintain access to and influence in the Arabian Peninsula and Persian Gulf as British
            forces prepared to withdraw; 10) the 1968 decision to establish a U.S. military facility
            on Diego Garcia, with British support, as a means of improving the overall Western
            military posture in the Indian Ocean; 11) the desire of the United States to preserve
            Iraq's political and social stability, thereby ensuring the contin-ued flow of oil and
            lessening the danger of inroads by Communists or radical Arab nationalists; and 12) U.S.
            efforts to rebuild relations with the Arab states after the Six-Day War.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
