<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v10">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume X, Cuba,
        January 1961–September 1962</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">Cuba, January 1961–September 1962</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume X</title>
    <editor role="primary">Louis J. Smith</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="statearchived"
        >http://www.state.gov/www/about_state/history/frusX/index.html</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1997</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1120</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the first months of the Kennedy
            administration a crisis arose over the final planning and launching of the failed
            invasion of the Bay of Pigs. The failure of the invasion led to a searching
            reexamination of Cuba policy. In addition, President Kennedy established a committee
            under former Army Chief of Staff General Maxwell Taylor and Attorney General Robert
            Kennedy to examine the causes of the defeat suffered at the Bay of Pigs. The editor has
            selected the primary documents relating to the policy reassessment, as well as the
            records of the most important testimony taken by the Taylor committee and the
            committee's ultimate report to the President. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The policy assessment initiated in May 1961
            led in November of that year to a decision to implement a new covert program to
            undermine and overthrow the Castro government in Cuba. This program was codenamed
            Operation Mongoose and much of the remainder of the volume after November 1961 is
            devoted to documenting Operation Mongoose. Oversight for Operation Mongoose was provided
            by the 5412/Special Group expanded to include General Taylor and Attorney General
            Kennedy. The focus of documentation selected on Operation Mongoose is on decisions made
            by the Special Group (Augmented) and their recommendations to President Kennedy. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Planning for Operation Mongoose was given
            additional impetus in the spring of 1962 by reports of expanded arms shipments from the
            Soviet Union to Cuba. The editor has included a selection of intelligence reports that
            indicated the growing concern in Washington over these shipments. These reports reveal a
            debate within the intelligence community in September over whether the Soviet weapons
            being introduced into Cuba included ballistic missiles with nuclear warheads. The volume
            concludes with clear warnings from the United States to the Soviet Union that the
            introduction of such weapons into Cuba would precipitate a major crisis in U.S.-Soviet
            relations. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
