<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v30">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XXX, Public
        Diplomacy</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Public Diplomacy</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXX</title>
    <editor role="primary">Kristin L. Ahlberg</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160933240</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2016</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2016</published-year>
    <published-date>2016-06-08</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1976</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">48</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">692</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the public diplomacy
            efforts of the Jimmy Carter administration. A major emphasis of the volume is the role
            the United States Information Agency (later the United States International
            Communication Agency) played in the formulation and implementation of public diplomacy.
            The volume documents the merger of the Department of State’s Bureau of Educational and
            Cultural Affairs (CU) and USIA in late 1977 and the establishment of ICA in early 1978
            and illustrates the varied efforts of USIA/ICA to conceptualize and administer a vast
            array of cultural initiatives and programming, including film and television programs,
            exhibits, and international conferences. Of note is the high-level documentation of
            USIA/ICA Director John Reinhardt, a former Ambassador who served in both USIA and the
            Department of State, and his efforts to engage with the USIA/ICA community during a time
            of transition. It also focuses on the Department of State’s public diplomacy efforts,
            notably people-to-people, cultural, and educational exchanges. The volume also
            chronicles Carter’s efforts, and those of his senior advisers, to manage the
            organizational and intellectual challenges posed by the CU–USIA merger and establishment
            of ICA and devise initiatives in support of the administration’s foreign policy.
        </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
