<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1977-80v26">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1977–1980, Volume XXVI, Arms
        Control and Nonproliferation</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1977-80" type="sub-series">1977–1980</title>
    <title type="volume">Arms Control and Nonproliferation</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXVI</title>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Chris Tudda</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>978016093099-7</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2015</published-year>
    <published-date>2015-11-19</published-date>
    <administration>carter</administration>
    <grouping administration="carter">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1977</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1980</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1314</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents the Carter
            administration’s multilateral, non-strategic arms control policy from 1977 until 1980.
            Topics include anti-satellite (ASAT) talks; chemical and biological warfare
            negotiations; conventional arms talks (CAT); nuclear non-proliferation, safeguards, and
            the International Fuel Cycle Evaluation program; comprehensive nuclear test-ban
            proposals and peaceful nuclear explosions; the United Nations Special Session on
            Disarmament; and nuclear non-proliferation in Latin America.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Carter administration’s priorities in
            arms control contrasted sharply with those of the Nixon and Ford administrations. Where
            his predecessors had concentrated on bilateral arms control negotiations with the Soviet
            Union, Carter aggressively pursued a range of multilateral agreements, with a strong
            emphasis on nonproliferation in nuclear and conventional arms. While Moscow remained the
            administration’s primary interlocutor, Carter worked closely with the United Kingdom to
            try to achieve a comprehensive nuclear test ban treaty. He also worked with Mexico to
            convince other Latin American nations to sign and/or ratify the Treaty of
            Tlatelolco—which had established Latin America as a nuclear-free zone in 1968. In
            conjunction with France, Japan, and other allies, Carter proposed the establishment of
            an International Fuel Cycle Evaluation program that would explore alternative nuclear
            fuel cycles containing materials not useable in nuclear weapons. The Carter
            administration also participated in multilateral arms control initiatives such as the
            1978 UN Special Session on Disarmament. Meanwhile, Carter tried to reduce the sale of
            conventional arms to allies with questionable human rights records.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">By the winter of 1979–80, however, the Soviet
            invasion of Afghanistan and other Soviet activities jeopardized Carter’s arms control
            initiatives. Reports of the use of chemical weapons by the Soviets in Afghanistan and
            Vietnam in Cambodia and Laos, the discovery of a 1979 outbreak of anthrax in a
            biological weapons factory in Sverdlovsk in the Soviet Union, and renewed Soviet nuclear
            tests led to administration protests that the Soviets had violated the 1972 Biological
            Weapons Convention and 1976 Threshold Test Ban Treaties respectively. The ASAT and CAT
            negotiations principally ended in early 1980, and the volume of U.S. conventional arms
            sales remained essentially unchanged during the administration.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
