<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v13">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XIII, Soviet
        Union, October 1970–October 1971</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Soviet Union, October 1970–October 1971</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XIII</title>
    <editor role="primary">David C. Geyer</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160791369</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year>2011</public-target-publication-year>
    <published-year>2011</published-year>
    <published-date>2011-09-30</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1970</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1971</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1129</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume continues the practice
            established in the previous <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> volume on
            U.S.-Soviet relations and focuses on the relationship in the global context,
            highlighting the conflicts and collaboration between the two superpowers on foreign
            policy issues from October 1970 to October 1971. Beginning with the confrontation over
            the construction of a Soviet military base in Cuba, the volume documents the development
            of the Nixon administration’s policy of détente and the crucial role of the private
            channel between Henry Kissinger, the President’s Assistant for National Security
            Affairs, and Soviet Ambassador Anatoly Dobrynin. The backchannel was key to making
            progress on the most problematic issues in U.S.-Soviet relations: Berlin, the war in
            Indochina, strategic arms limitation talks, Jewish emigration from the Soviet Union, and
            trade. It also allowed the two nations to avoid conflict and to cooperate on managing
            crises around the world, such as the Middle East dispute and the Indo-Pakistani
            conflict.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The Nixon administration’s opening to China,
            beginning with Kissinger’s secret trip to Beijing in July 1971 and the subsequent
            announcement of Nixon’s visit to China, was a policy decision that required careful
            handling in the context of U.S.-Soviet relations. This volume documents the discussions
            within the administration of the impact on the relationship of the initiative, as well
            as Kissinger’s management of that impact in his discussions with Dobrynin.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As Kissinger’s prestige and importance to the
            superpower relationship grew, the Department of State was increasingly sidelined in the
            formulation and execution of U.S. policy in significant foreign affairs issues. The
            discussions between Nixon and Kissinger, many captured in Presidential tape recordings,
            on how to handle Secretary of State William Rogers’s attempts to reassert the
            Department’s authority are among the documents in the volume.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The volume also includes documentation on the
            internal and bilateral negotiations for the timing of a visit by Nixon to the Soviet
            Union and ends with the public announcement in October 1971 of the May 1972 summit
            between Nixon and Brezhnev, the first U.S.-Soviet summit since 1967. The era of détente
            and cooperation between the superpowers had begun.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
