<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v26">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume XXVI,
        Arab-Israeli Dispute, 1974–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Arab-Israeli Dispute, 1974–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXVI</title>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13>9780160829987</isbn13>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2012</published-year>
    <published-date>2012-08-15</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1974</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">26</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1094</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The focus of this volume is the negotiations
            leading to the two disengagement agreements between Egypt and Israel and the one
            disengagement agreement between Syria and Israel. The end of the October 1973 War left
            the Egyptian and Israeli armies interlocked in the Sinai and Israeli and Syrian armies
            interlocked in the Golan Heights. This provided Secretary of State Henry Kissinger, who
            had taken the lead role in negotiations concerning the Arab-Israeli dispute after the
            October 1973 War, the opportunity to negotiate landmark agreements between Israel and
            two of its Arab neighbors in the months following the war. Initial discussions between
            Kissinger and Arab leaders began in November 1973 (coverage of this is found in <tei:ref
                target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v25">
                <tei:hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi>, 1969–1976, volume XXV,
                Arab-Israeli Crisis and War, 1973</tei:ref>) and culminated in formal disengagement
            agreements beginning in 1974. Kissinger preferred these disengagement agreements instead
            of a comprehensive agreement as a way to create a relationship between the Israelis and
            Egyptians and Syrians that could lead to a future comprehensive settlement of the
            Arab-Israeli dispute. Additionally, he argued that this more modest step-by-step
            approach would prevent individual crises, such as terrorist attacks, to sidetrack
            negotiations. Accordingly, this volume documents the development of this step-by-step
            approach beginning with the first disengagement agreement between the Israelis and
            Egyptians in January 1974, the only disengagement agreement between the Israelis and
            Syrians in May 1974, and the second disengagement agreement between the Israelis and
            Egyptians in September 1975.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume also documents the U.S. response
            to the outbreak of civil war in Lebanon. This final chapter begins with the U.S.
            Government’s observation of the war in the fall of 1975, but focuses primarily on the
            period after the disintegration of the Lebanese army in March 1976, followed by the
            evacuation of U.S. embassy personnel, and concludes in August 1976 with a strategy
            session between Kissinger and U.S. ambassadors to the Middle East.</tei:p>
    </summary>
    <created-by>admin</created-by>
    <created-datetime>2010-06-28T15:09:31.753-04:00</created-datetime>
    <last-modified-by>wicentowskijc</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-datetime>2011-10-14T14:40:14.194-04:00</last-modified-datetime>
    <release-status-code>released</release-status-code>
    <released-by>wicentowskijc</released-by>
    <release-datetime>2011-10-14T14:40:14.194-04:00</release-datetime>
    <recalled-by/>
    <recall-datetime/>
</volume>
