<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v29p2">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XXIX, Part 2,
        Japan</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Japan</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XXIX, Part 2</title>
    <editor role="primary">Karen L. Gatz</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/johnsonlb/xxix2/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2006</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">35</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">330</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents U.S. policy toward
            Japan during a period of increasing change in the relations between the two allies.
            Japan was fast becoming a major economic power while still relying on the United States
            for its security. A theme of the coverage, in fact, is the ongoing U.S. effort to
            encourage Japan to assume a greater role in its own military defense and to play a
            greater role on the world stage, especially in terms of the economic development of the
            rest of Asia. Another major theme is U.S. efforts to encourage the continuation of a
            moderate, pro-Western Japanese Government. The creation of a joint U.S.-Japanese
            economic planning group sought to coordinate the two economies. The eventual reversion
            of U.S. administered-Ryukyus to Japan was a goal of Japanese Governments, but it played
            out during this period in the successful effort by Japan to regain control in 1968 from
            the United States of the much less strategically significant Bonin Islands. A related
            theme was domestic Japanese opposition to the war in Vietnam and the use of U.S. bases
            in Japan to support the U.S. campaign in Vietnam. A final theme is the successful U.S.
            discouragement of closer Japanese-People’s Republic of China relations.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
