<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76ve11p1">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume E–11, Part 1,
        Documents on Mexico; Central America; and the Caribbean, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">Documents on Mexico; Central America; Caribbean, 1973–1976</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume E–11, Part 1</title>
    <editor role="primary">Halbert Jones</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Douglas Kraft</editor>
    <editor role="general">Adam M. Howard</editor>
    <external-location loc=""/>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="epub"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2015</published-year>
    <published-date>2015-06-03</published-date>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1973</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">46</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">1232</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume is part of a <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</tei:hi> subseries that documents the most important
            issues in the foreign policy of Presidents Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. The
            volume on American Republics has been divided into two parts: Part One, this volume,
            documents the formulation of a new U.S. policy towards the region as a whole and
            bilateral relations with fourteen countries and one British possession—The Bahamas,
            Barbados, Belize, Costa Rica, Cuba, the Dominican Republic, El Salvador, Grenada,
            Guatemala, Guyana, Haiti, Honduras, Jamaica, Mexico, and Nicaragua—during the second
            Nixon and Ford administrations; Part Two, forthcoming, documents bilateral relations
            with countries in South America.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. policy towards Latin America during this
            period centered on establishing what Henry A. Kissinger called a “New Dialogue” with the
            region. Launched in October 1973, just days after Kissinger took office as Secretary of
            State, the “New Dialogue” was envisioned as a constructive way for the United States to
            meet the challenge posed by the perceived emergence of a Latin American regional bloc.
            The initiative called for regular meetings of foreign ministers to address issues of
            mutual concern and aimed to restore a sense that a special relationship existed between
            the United States and its neighbors to the south. By 1976, however, U.S. officials had
            largely abandoned the idea of pursuing a unified regional policy, as called for by the
            “New Dialogue.” Instead, recognizing that Latin America was not a monolithic bloc, the
            Ford administration focused more on bilateral relations with the nations of the
            hemisphere. As this volume documents, during the Nixon and Ford administrations
            immigration and narcotics control emerged as key issues in bilateral relations,
            particularly with Mexico. Other themes that occur are water salinity, economic concerns,
            and investment disputes. Finally, military regimes controlled many Central American
            governments during the 1970s, and some early hints of the unrest that generated the
            civil wars of the 1980s appear in the documents in this volume. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
