<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1969-76v05">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1969–1976, Volume V, United
        Nations, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1969-76" type="sub-series">1969–1976</title>
    <title type="volume">United Nations, 1969–1972</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume V</title>
    <editor role="primary">Evan M. Duncan</editor>
    <editor role="general">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/nixon/v/index.htm</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2004</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>nixon-ford</administration>
    <grouping administration="nixon-ford">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1969</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1976</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">37</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">940</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The editor of the volume sought to present
            documentation illuminating responsibility for major foreign policy decisions of the U.S.
            Government, with emphasis on the President and his principal foreign policy advisers.
            The documents include memoranda and records of discussions, telegrams, policy papers,
            and other documents that set forth policy issues and options and show decisions or
            actions taken. The emphasis is on the development of U.S. policy and on major aspects
            and repercussions of its execution rather than on the details of policy execution. </tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">While United Nations affairs were not a high
            priority during the Nixon administration, they were a major concern for the Department
            of State. While two key issues, the question of Chinese representation and the selection
            of a new Secretary-General to succeed U Thant, rose to the level of high interest, most
            UN issues fell below the purview of the upper echelons of the Nixon administration’s
            foreign policy leadership. Furthermore, President Nixon and his Assistant for National
            Security Affairs Henry Kissinger both believed that they were realists more concerned
            with national self-interest and major power relationships than with political, social,
            and economic issues of the United Nations. Both Nixon and Kissinger were skeptical of
            the effectiveness and value of the United Nations. They therefore devoted scant
            attention to a organization dominated by smaller and developing nations and replete with
            specialized international organizations. Nixon and Kissinger did recognize that the
            United Nations was the most important and visible world organization and therefore could
            not be totally ignored. It could even be used to provided a useful and high-profile
            venue to support U.S. foreign policies. For these reasons the two issues that the Nixon
            administration believed were vitally important, Chinese representation in the United
            Nations and the selection of a new Secretary-General, are given the most coverage in the
            volume. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
