<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1958-60v10p2">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1958–1960, Eastern Europe;
        Finland; Greece; Turkey, Volume X, Part 2</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1958-60" type="sub-series">1958–1960</title>
    <title type="volume">Eastern Europe; Finland; Greece; Turkey</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume X, Part 2</title>
    <editor role="primary">Ronald D. Landa</editor>
    <editor role="primary">James E. Miller</editor>
    <editor role="primary">William F. Sanford, Jr.</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Sherrill Brown Wells</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="madison"
        >http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS195860v10p2</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1993</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>eisenhower</administration>
    <grouping administration="eisenhower">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1958</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1960</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">28</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">926</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume documents U.S. foreign policy
            related to East-West exchanges, Albania, Bulgaria, Finland, Greece, Poland, Turkey, and
            Yugoslavia during the final three years of the Eisenhower administration.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">During the years 1958–1960, the Department of
            State worked closely with the White House in the formulation of U.S. policy toward
            East-West exchanges, the individual states of Eastern Europe, Finland, Greece, and
            Turkey. Secretaries of State John Foster Dulles and Christian A. Herter advised
            President Eisenhower in detail and had major roles in the deliberations of the National
            Security Council. The White House and National Security Council directed the preparation
            of reports based on interagency information on these areas. This volume contains
            memoranda of discussion and policy papers of the National Security Council with respect
            to basic U.S. policies. The Department of State prepared and coordinated exchanges of
            views and discussions of policy toward Cyprus with the British Government and its
            officers participated in the meetings between President Eisenhower and Premier Nikita S.
            Khrushchev in September 1959.</tei:p>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This volume also presents memoranda of
            conversation and records of meetings between the President and his principal foreign
            policy advisers, including National Security Council meetings, institutional NSC
            documents, informal foreign policy materials, White House documents, policy
            recommendations by the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and internal U.S. Government policy
            recommendations and decision papers.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
