<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1964-68v12">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968, Volume XII, Western
        Europe</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1964-68" type="sub-series">1964–1968</title>
    <title type="volume">Western Europe</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XII</title>
    <editor role="primary">James E. Miller</editor>
    <editor role="general">David S. Patterson</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/johnsonlb/xii/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>2001</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>johnson</administration>
    <grouping administration="johnson">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1964</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1968</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">35</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">765</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation printed in this volume
            highlights the central role of the Department of State in bilateral policy formulation
            toward individual Western European nations and Canada. The documentation on Denmark
            focuses on Danish nuclear policy on Greenland and a supplementary understanding reached
            between the United States and Denmark on their 1951 Defense of Greenland agreement in
            the aftermath of the crash of a nuclear-armed U.S. B-52 bomber near Thule Air Force Base
            in Greenland. Documentation on France is more comprehensive and includes Franco-American
            differences, primarily those stemming from President de Gaulle's actions concerning
            NATO, as well as differences over Cuba, Southeast Asia, and the People's Republic of
            China. The documentation on Italy reflects U.S. interest in the internal political scene
            in Italy at the outset of the center-left coalition period, as well as developments in
            the Italian Communist Party. The documentation on Portugal highlights U.S. concerns
            about the policies of the Salazar regime in Africa. With regard to Spain, the documents
            focus on negotiations over renewal of U.S. base rights in Spain as well as Spain's
            thoughts about its future relationships with Western Europe in general and the European
            Economic Community in particular. The documentation on the United Kingdom is a tour
            d'horizon of economic, political, and defense issues. The main topics include the
            sterling crisis, British plans to pull back "East of Suez," and Anglo-American
            differences over Vietnam. Also included in this volume is documentation on the Vatican,
            which reflects the Holy See's increasing concern about the conflict in Vietnam and the
            Pope's efforts to mediate the conflict. Extensive consultations on Vietnam are also
            highlighted in the documentation on Canada, but there is also an important focus on
            trade, Law of the Sea, and fisheries issues. </tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
