<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<volume id="frus1961-63v12">
    <title type="complete">Foreign Relations of the United States, 1961–1963, Volume XII, American
        Republics</title>
    <title type="series">Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
    <title n="1961-63" type="sub-series">1961–1963</title>
    <title type="volume">American Republics</title>
    <title type="volume-number">Volume XII</title>
    <editor role="primary">Edward C. Keefer</editor>
    <editor role="primary">Harriet Dashiell Schwar</editor>
    <editor role="primary">W. Taylor Fain III</editor>
    <editor role="general">Glenn W. LaFantasie</editor>
    <external-location loc="state"
        >http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ho/frus/kennedyjf/xii/</external-location>
    <isbn10/>
    <isbn13/>
    <media type="print"/>
    <publication-status>published</publication-status>
    <public-target-publication-year/>
    <published-year>1996</published-year>
    <published-date/>
    <administration>kennedy</administration>
    <grouping administration="kennedy">regular</grouping>
    <coverage type="from">1961</coverage>
    <coverage type="to">1963</coverage>
    <length>
        <span part="front" unit="pages">31</span>
        <span part="body" unit="pages">913</span>
    </length>
    <summary>
        <tei:p xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The documentation printed in this volume
            focuses on U.S. policy toward the American Republics of the Caribbean, Central, and
            South America. The guiding principle for selection was high-level interest within the
            Kennedy administration in policy and relations toward a specific country. This focus
            tends to give more coverage to countries in which there were crisis or specific problems
            and de-emphasizes countries that had basically good relations with the United States
            during the period. Documents were selected that highlight policy discussions within the
            U.S. Government, with particular emphasis on the highest level at which policy on a
            particular subject was determined, that revealed policy positions and internal
            differences over policy, and that summarized developments or positions regarding an
            issue. Records of conversations with foreign leaders both abroad and in Washington were
            selected to illuminate U.S. relations with those countries. Embassy reportage is limited
            to particularly significant cables that may have influenced or contributed to the making
            of U.S. policy at critical points. A number of relevant documents that conveyed finished
            intelligence to U.S. policymakers, in particular National Intelligence Estimates and
            Special National Intelligence Estimates, are included.</tei:p>
    </summary>
</volume>
